where
ี่
Academia Sinica's February Posture Response Lectures Begin
中央研究院二月份姿势响应演讲会开始
We invite Wang Huijun, Vice President to host for us
我们请王慧君,副院长为我们主持
Good night, fellow friends
各位同人朋友晚安
I haven't been here to chair this meeting in four years
我已經四年沒有來主持這個會議了
So now it is returned by the central government
所以現在被中央交回來
i'm still a little nervous
我還是有點緊張
I haven't done this for a long time
很久沒有做這個事情
but today is very happy
不過今天很高興
We have invited Professor Xie Qinghe
我們有請到謝清和教授
Also our researcher
也是我們的研究員
come here and give us a great talk
來這邊跟我們做一個很精彩的演講
His field is of course related to so-called stem cells
他的領域當然是跟所謂的幹細胞
very tight matter
很夯的事情有關係
So I thought this wonderfully polite
所以我想這個精彩客氣
But before this starts
不過在這個開始之前
I'm going to make a teaser
我要做一個預告
because I always forget
因為我每次都會忘掉
In fact, there will be the next feast of knowledge in March
其實3月份也有下次的知識饗宴
It is told by our chief medical doctor
是由我們主經醫院士來講
Causes and consequences of economic inequality in Taiwan
台灣經濟不公平的前因後果
So this is also a topic of great concern to everyone.
所以這個也是一個大家很關心的題目
So I hope March 29
所以希望3月29號
Please take part
請大家踴躍參加
Today I would like to introduce Professor Xie Qinghe a little
今天我要稍微介紹一下謝清和教授
I haven't known Professor Xie for long.
我跟謝教授認識不是很久
but very impressive
但是非常的印象深刻
In fact, Professor Xie is also an outstanding cardiologist.
其實謝教授也是一個很傑出的心臟科醫師
So he can actually see a doctor
所以他其實還是能看診
It's just that there is less time now
只是現在時間比較少一點
he spent a lot of time
他花了很多時間
are doing related research now
現在都在做相關的研究
Today's topic is also related to the heart
今天題目也是跟心臟有關係的
Dr. Xie and Professor Xie graduated from the Department of Medicine, Kaohsiung Medical College
謝醫師、謝教授是高雄醫學院醫學系畢業
Go to National Taiwan University after graduation
畢業了以後到台大
After studying at National Taiwan University as a specialist doctor
念的在台大做了專科醫師以後
Later, it should be on this
後來應該是這上面都有
Went to America in 1990
1990年到美國去
toWashingtonUniversity
到Washington University
Is that the one in Seattle?
是西雅圖那個嗎?
from Seattle
是西雅圖的
because there is another
因為還有另外一個
at Washington University in Saint Louis
在Washington University在Saint Louis
Medicine is also good
醫學方也生好
This medical school has learned some of the most advanced research related to stem cells
這個醫學院就學了最先進關於乾細胞相關的一些研究
So he is considered a very outstanding researcher in Taiwan.
所以他這方面在臺灣也算是非常傑出的研究員
We're in a national achievement program called the Biotech Medicine Program
我們在一個國家成績計畫叫生技醫藥計畫裡面
We also set up a team related to stem cells
我們也成立了一個關於乾細胞相關的團隊
He is the leader of the big team, the leader
他是大團隊的領導者、leader
Therefore, it has made a great contribution to the research related to stem cells in Taiwan.
所以對於臺灣乾細胞相關的研究有非常大的貢獻
He has also won many awards, including the dismissal of the Ministry of Science and Technology of the National Science Council, etc.
他也得過很多的獎包括解除國科會的科技部的解除獎等等
also published quite a few papers
也發表相當多的論文
Many of them are in very high-end journals
很多都是在非常高檔的期刊上面
He also has a very special biotechnology fund
他也是有一個很特殊的生技基金
Foundation Award Winners
基金會的得獎者
This foundation seems to give 20 million at a time
這個基金會一次好像給兩千萬
or what information
還是什麼什麼資料
25 million
兩千五百萬
a lot of money
很多錢
But give them ten years to do the research
不過給他們十年好好去做研究
So we look forward to having such a good environment
所以我們期待有這樣子好的環境
He is now a researcher at our biomedical institute
他現在在我們的生醫所當研究員
Well but also too big
那麼但是也是太大的
This is a difficult merger professor
這個算是艱難合併教授
So since he's trying to keep his doctor's license
所以因為他要保住他的醫師的執照
must go to the hospital to see a doctor
一定要到醫院去看病
We don't have hospitals in Central Plains
我們中原沒有醫院
So he still has to go to National Taiwan University to see a doctor
所以他還是要到台大去看病
Then we are like this age
那我們像這把年紀
The most concerned thing is the doctor
最關心的就是醫生
So we all please the doctor
所以我們都會討好醫師
because we need their care
因為我們需要他們的照顧
so this
所以這個
but the doctor
但是醫生
I think we Taiwanese doctors all know
我想我們台灣醫生大家都知道
are very very busy
都非常非常的忙
He is waiting in the morning
他早上排著病號
A row to more than one hundred
一排排到一百多號
I don't know how these doctors see a doctor
我搞不清楚他們這些醫生怎麼看病
But he still does state-of-the-art research despite his busy schedule
不過他在百忙之中還是做最先進的研究
The progress of our kind of medicine
這個對我們這種醫學的進步
does play an important role
的確扮演很重要的角色
So we have this anticipation today
所以我們今天懷著這個期待的心情
Come and listen to our Professor Xie tell us about this
來聽聽我們謝教授跟我們講這個
The Dream Chasing and Rhapsody of a Physician-Scientist
一個醫師科學家的追夢與狂想
Regeneration
心機再生
we warmly welcome
我們熱烈歡迎
Thank you very much for the introduction of the vice president
非常謝謝副院長的介紹
Thank you very much all the guests
也非常感謝各位來賓
Seniors and everyone
各位前輩以及各位
Colleagues in our hospital
我們院裡面的同仁
in relatively cold
在相對比較冷
And it's raining again
而且又在下雨的天氣裡面
come to our events
還來參加我們的活動
The vice president politely said he would be nervous
副院長很客氣說他會緊張
If the deputy dean is nervous
那副院長如果會緊張
Then I'm more nervous, really nervous
那我更緊張 真的很緊張
Because usually if the author in the audience
因為通常如果說台下的作者
They are all like vice-presidents, like secretary-general and academicians.
都是像副院長 像秘書長院士這樣
Actually, I'm not nervous at all.
其實我一點都不會緊張這樣
But when I found out that what the audience did was our normal
可是當發現說台下做的是我們一般的
In fact, there are many professors here
還有其實在這邊有很多的教授
There are also many of our left and right neighbors
那也有很多的我們的左右鄰居
We even came up to Peng Chang from Taichung and Kaohsiung
甚至有我們竟然從台中同高雄上來彭長
Then I just saw outside
然後我剛才在外面有看到
There are many students from Jianzhong here
有建中的學弟很多位在這邊
I'm most afraid of this kind of speech
我最怕這種演講
Because this kind of speech is usually a little difficult
因為這種演講通常有一點難
a little challenging
有一些挑戰性
How can these messages be
怎麼樣可以把這些訊息
which we want to share with you
這些我們想要分享給大家的
There are even some that you can let everyone know
甚至有一些可以讓大家知道
Then we can even promote things together
然後可以甚至大家一起來推動的事情
how to convey it
怎麼樣把它傳達出去
can then cause an interaction
然後可以引起互動
It's actually quite a challenge
這其實是一個蠻大的挑戰
probably next to a little bit
大概僅次於一點點就
I went to the Taichung Science and Technology Museum twice before
以前有兩次經驗到台中科博館去
Taichung Science and Technology Museum to give a science and technology speech
台中科博館去做科博演講
Usually the audience is from 4 years old to 80 years old
通常那個聽眾都是從4歲一直到80歲都有
That challenge is also very high.
那個挑戰性也很高這樣
Later, I really wanted to say that I just brought some toys to
後來我都很想說我隨便帶一些玩具去
go help like this
去幫忙一下這樣
So today I want to introduce to you
那今天就是要跟各位介紹
Regeneration
心機再生
I remember 16 years ago
我記得16年前的時候
At that time, the general manager of our former health insurance bureau once
那時候有一次我們前健保局的總經理
Professor Zhang Hongren
張宏仁教授
He is after resigning from the Health Insurance Bureau
他就是健保局卸任之後
then go to harvard medical school
然後到哈佛醫學院去
To visit a scholar like this
去訪問學者這樣子
He had one please at that time
他有一支請在那個時候的
backyard rescue over there
在那邊的博士後院救援
we eat together
大家一起吃飯
everyone will chat
大家就會聊天
He asked me what I was doing
他就問我說我在做什麼
I said I was doing rejuvenation
我說我在做心機再生
He asked me, is it possible to regenerate the mind?
他就問我說心機再生有可能嗎
So I still ask every day to this day
所以我到今天還是每天再問說
Is it possible for Xinji to be alive?
新積在生有可能嗎
It seems like a dream to me
這對我來講好像是一個夢想
Sometimes it's about chasing your dreams
有時候要去追求你的夢想
need to be a little fanatic like this
需要有一點點狂熱這樣
This is not madness
這個不是狂妄的狂熱
It really means fanatical
是真的有 狂熱的意思
not arrogant
不是狂妄的
So let's see today if we can
所以今天就看看說我們能不能
Let this new accumulation be born this big challenge
就把這個新積在生這個很大的挑戰
can be pushed forward
可以往前推
may even one day reach one of its goals
甚至有一天可以達到它的一個目標
Thank you very much Vice President just now
剛剛很謝謝副院長
Introduce a little background of mine
稍微介紹我的一個background
In fact, the main thing I want to share with you is
其實主要要跟各位分享的是
I went to four medical schools after I read it
我看完之後我念了四個醫學院
Everyone knows that our medical school in Taiwan takes seven years
大家知道我們在台灣的醫學院要七年
after seven years of medical school
七年的醫學院之後
It took two years to carry out the national duty
花了兩年的時間去進行國民的義務
Obligation to serve as a soldier
當兵的義務
five years of residency
還有五年的住院醫師
So another seven years
所以又七年開始
know after seven years
七年之後知道說
So that's what heart surgery is all about.
原來心臟手術是這一門一回事
Then come to the United States to study BHD
然後來就到美國去念BHD
do doctoral research
做博士學研究
Add up exactly seven years
加起來正好也是七年
then come back after
然後回來之後
City University
一開始在城大
From assistant researcher to associate researcher
從助研究員 副研究員到
Assistant Professor Associate Professor to Professor
助理教授 副教授到教授
another seven years
又是七年
I think being a professor is actually learning.
我覺得當教授其實也是在學習
really like a student
真是像學生一樣
So seventy percent and four equal twenty-eight
所以七成與四等於二十八
So until now it seems like
所以到現在好像才覺得說
Seems like a student
好像學生當了差不多的
See if there is any way I can help others like this
看看有沒有辦法可以幫忙別人這樣子
good
好
That's because the topic is a
那因為這個題目是一個
How do physician-scientists pursue this dream
醫師科學家怎麼樣去追這個夢想
So I will simply introduce to you
所以我很簡單的跟各位介紹一下
i grow up
我一些成長
And the process of chasing dreams like this
還有這些追夢的過程這樣子
usually means
通常就是說
after medical school
醫學院畢業之後
We now have more and more young
我們現在有越來越多的年輕的
friend young schoolboy sister
朋友 年輕的學弟妹妹
they will want to study and do research
他們會想要去學做研究
In the education of our medical schools in Taiwan
我們台灣的醫學院的教育裡面
Generally speaking, there is a lack of basic research
一般來說比較缺少基礎研究的部分
Abroad is a little different
國外是有點點不太一樣
so everyone will meet
所以大家就會遇到
I'm often asked a question that says
我常常被問一個問題就是說
if he is interested in research
如果他對研究有興趣
want to go to that doctor
想要去那個博士
Do you want to go out after graduating from a college?
到底是要在一學院畢業就出去呢
Or do you go out after your residency?
還是說當完住院醫師再出去
There are pros and cons to each
這其實各有利弊的
Because I left after graduating from college
因為一學院畢業就出去
Of course younger
當然比較年輕嘛
But if you want to come back to Taiwan
可是如果你要回來台灣
After you get your Ph.D., you will do research and then come back.
你拿到博士做完博士會研究再回來
already old
已經老了
Becoming a resident doctor may not be enough
要當住院醫師可能沒力了
So this is something to consider
所以這個是一個要考量的
But if you say that you finished your residency in Taiwan
但你如果說在台灣做完住院醫師
Our cumulative experience is good
我們累計的是經驗很好
But I haven't been a student for more than ten years since I left
可是出去之後已經十幾年沒當學生
It's hard work being a student again
再重新當學生也很辛苦
So there are pros and cons to each
所以其實各有利弊
Just look at each person's situation and make a trade-off
就看看說每個人的狀況怎麼樣去做取捨
clinical
臨床
So I'm staying as a resident
所以我是留下來當住院醫師
After that, after getting a specialist
那結束之後拿到專科醫師之後
Then the next question is to say
那下一個問題就是說
Then I will continue to be an attending physician
那我要繼續去當主治醫師
Or do I chase my dreams
還是說我要追我的夢想
Go abroad to study for a doctorate
去國外念一個博士這樣
Then choose to go out
後來是選擇出去
because it really is one
因為就真的就是一個
It's been like this since I was a child
從小的夢想這樣子
good
好
then i choose
那我是選擇
Seattle
後來是到西亞圖
Go to Utter Mission Wash's business project to go to this field
到Utter Mission Wash的生意工程去這個領域
It was so simple when I thought about it
當時會這樣子想其實很簡單
Because there are actually a lot of implantable medical devices in Xinzang Surgery
因為新藏外科裡面其實有很多的植入性的這些醫療器材
You may have heard of artificial escorts
各位可能聽過人工伴摩
Vascular Stent
血管的支架
artificial blood vessels
還有人工的血管
even an artificial heart
甚至人工心臟
And the well-known Yekemo
還有大家很熟悉的葉克摩
Is Ye Kemo Doctor Ye?
葉克摩是不是葉醫師
Not a doctor surnamed Ye
不是姓葉的醫師
Yekemo is an instrument doing extracorporeal circulation
葉克摩是一個儀器是在做體外循環的
These things are business engineering people
這些東西都是生意工程的人
develop it for clinical use
把它發展出來可以在臨床上使用的
However, although these have been used clinically for decades
不過這些雖然我們已經在臨床上用了幾十年
it has some problems
它都有一些問題
we hope to make it better
我們希望可以把它做得更好
So I wanted to say
所以當初就想說
If I can combine engineering to do biomedical research
我如果能夠去結合工程來做生物醫學的研究
may be helpful
可能會有幫助
So this is the time to choose
所以這是那個時候去選
Reasons to study bioengineering
去念生物生意工程的原因
Then Dr.
那後來博士
When I'm about to get my Ph.D.
快拿到博士的學位的時候
But once I came back to National Taiwan University to give a speech
但是有一次有回來台大演講
Then my teacher, Professor Lin Fangyi, said
那我的老師林芳一教授就說
do you want to come back
你要不要回來了
At that time I thought
那當時我是覺得說
Seems like I learned a little bit by doing research
好像做研究才學到一點點皮毛
I want to be doing a lot of seniors are
我想在做很多前輩都
have more experience than me
都比我很多的經驗
I just started reading
那我剛開始去念
After entering the laboratory, I found out that
去進實驗室以後才發現說
In fact, doing research is not so simple
其實做研究沒那麼簡單
as if we
就好像我們
When Dr. Zhu Yuan wants to learn to be a surgeon
朱元醫師要學當一個外科醫師的時候
At the beginning, you must start by learning to brush your hands first.
一開始一定從先學刷手開始
Avoid infection by brushing hands
因為刷手避免感染
Then you start sewing the skin
然後你開始會開始縫皮膚
Slowly start cutting the fence
慢慢會開始割欄圍
nothing to do with that politics
跟那個政治沒有關係
Start with the simplest operation
就從最簡單的手術開始做
Then slowly start to dye until the end like this
然後慢慢的開始進染到最後這樣
In fact, doing research is like this
其實做研究也是這樣子
wait a minute before we continue
等一下我們再繼續講
So I feel like my PhD is not enough
所以我覺得我PhD好像還不夠
So I went to Boston
所以後來又去到波斯登
go do boso research
去做博索研究
After doing that, the next question is to say
做完之後下一個問題就是說
Do I stay in the U.S. to find a job or do I come back?
我到底要留在美國找工作還是要回來
Then I chose to come back
那後來我是選擇回來的這樣
good
好
Why did you go this way?
為什麼會走這樣的路呢
In fact, there are still some antecedents and consequences
其實還是有一些前因後果
there is usually some reason for everything
凡是通常都會有一些原因
There are some steps into the group
有一些邁入可群
i liked it when i was young
我小時候喜歡
likes to shake
喜歡弄動弄息的
I like doing things by hand, I don't like studying
喜歡動手做不喜歡念書
my wife will find it strange
我太太會覺得奇怪
You don't seem to like doing housework that much at home
你在家裡面好像沒有那麼喜歡做家事
you would love to move when you were a kid
你小時候會喜歡動的
Actually, I really like to move my hands and feet.
其實我真的蠻喜歡動手動腳
I just like to do things with my hands
就是喜歡動手做一些事情
When I was a student
以前在學生時代的時候
I seem to be doing pretty well in the lab classes.
我實驗課的都好像學得還不錯
When it comes time to memorize
一到要背書那種
my grades are not good
我成績就不太好
So this is also natural
所以這個也很自然
I'm going for surgery
我就是去走外科
Will undergo cardiac surgery because
會走心臟外科是因為
In my fourth year of medical school
在醫學院四年級的時候
One of them went to Chang Gung Hospital as an intern
有一支去看到去長庚醫院見習
I saw Professor Zhang Zhaoxiong, the then president of Chang Gung Hospital
看到當時長庚醫院院長張昭雄教授
he is undergoing open heart surgery
他在做開心手術
i feel amazing
我覺得非常神奇
i adore him so much
我非常要崇拜他
I find it amazing that
我覺得很神奇的是
a heart is beating
一個心臟在跳
Our technology through extracorporeal circulation
我們透過體外循環的技術
freeze this heart heart paralysis
把這個心臟冷凍 心臟麻痺
stop the heart
讓心臟停下來
then open the heart
然後把心臟打開
after getting hands and feet inside
在裡面動手動腳之後
This heart problem can be mended
可以修補這個心臟的問題
Then bring the temperature back up
然後再把體溫回升
swim the blood back
把血液再逛回去
heart beats again
心臟又重新跳起來
and after closing the chest
然後把胸關起來之後
can solve this problem
居然可以解決這個問題
To me it's really a miraculous thing
對我來講這實在是一件很神奇的事情
So I thought I'd go with this one
所以我就覺得我要走這一顆
At that time, it was actually quite large
那個時候其實是有點廣大
But then I really went this way
不過後來就真的走的這一條路
But once you walk in
可是一旦走進去之後
Until I finished my clinical training at National Taiwan University
一直到我在台大完成我的臨床訓練之後
just feel like saying
就覺得說
This life is really wonderful
這生命實在是很奧妙
why
為什麼呢
Because in fact when I
因為 其實當我一顆
Every day we have to fight with life
每天我們都要跟生命搏鬥嘛
It may be hard for you guys to imagine us
各位可能很難想像我們
now everyone is talking
現在大家都在講說
your working hours
你工作時間
Then we have to fight for this leisure time and so on.
然後要爭取這個休閒的時間之類的
The previous training of Xinjiang Surgery may still be the same now
新疆外科以前的training 現在可能還是一樣
Even Saturdays and Sundays are all counted as holidays
就是連禮拜六禮拜天假日通通都算
The average work day is 16 hours
每天平均工作是16個小時
So it is very common to work continuously for more than 30 hours
所以30幾個小時連續工作這個是很常見的
It is also common to have to fight with life and death every day
每天要跟生死搏鬥這個也很常見
sometimes we can
有些時候我們就可以
save our patients
把我們的病人救起來
But sometimes we just can't be that good
但有些時候我們就沒辦法那麼厲害
some patients we lose them
有些病人我們就會失去他們
usually means
通常就是說
How we lost these patients we probably all know why
我們怎麼失去這些病人我們大概都會知道說他是哪些原因
So we want to say that we have the opportunity to do better in the future
所以我們希望說將來有機會可以做得更好
But sometimes even if we feel that the patient may not have a chance, he probably
不過有些時候即使我們覺得這個病人可能沒有機會的他大概
maybe we can't save him
可能我們沒辦法救他
He can ride a mech again
他居然又可以騎機士的這樣子
rescued by us
被我們救起來活過來
it's weird
這很奇怪
Losing patients sometimes we don't know very well
失去病人有的時候我們不是很清楚
sometimes
有時候
Rescue the patient We are not so clear why we can save him
救活病人我們也不太不是那麼清楚為什麼可以把他救起來
so feel like saying
所以覺得說
I am really in awe of life, there are many
真的是很敬畏生命有很多
what we don't know
我們不了解的地方
So I'm wondering if there's a way we can learn more about
所以我在想說我們有沒有辦法更了解
Because usually the more you know about a thing
因為通常你越了解一件事情
Even a scientific study is the same
即使是一個科學研究都一樣
The more you understand why it's what it's mechanism
你越了解它的原因 它的機制是什麼
then you might have a better chance
那你可能就有更好的機會
better treatments can be devised to help it
可以去設計更好的治療來幫助它
it was a simple idea
這當時很簡單的想法
So I went to America
所以後來就去美國
then i'm in seattle
那我再西亞圖
So everyone, Seattle is on the northwest side of the United States.
那各位 西亞圖是在美國的西北邊
It’s very close to Taiwan, and you can get there by direct flight from EVA Air.
離台灣很近 長榮航空直飛就可以到了這樣
Then just like when we were young
然後就像大家年輕的時候
Many have the same experience, the same dream
很多有同樣的經歷 同樣的夢想
It is said that many campuses in the United States are very beautiful.
說美國的校園很多都很漂亮這樣
That's some views of Seattle like this
那是西亞圖的一些景色這樣
I want to say everyone come here after dinner
我想說大家吃完飯來這裡
Just to show you some pretty pictures
只要讓你們看一些漂亮的圖畫
So this is the Space Needle, everyone knows it better.
所以這個是太空針 這個大家比較清楚
that's mount rainier
那是雷尼爾山
this is a national park
這是國家公園
That's some scenery of the school
那是學校的一些景色
So you can also see cherry blossoms in spring
所以春天的時候看也看櫻花
In autumn, you can watch the windy night
秋天的時候可以看風夜
really can see
還真的都看得到
But it's beautiful
不過講得很美
In fact, it was quite painful at the beginning of the doctoral program.
其實剛開始念博士班是蠻痛苦的
is crying beautifully
是哭得很美
it's been like this
一直開始這樣子
the first one
第一個就
Although I am a graduate of medical school
雖然我是醫學院的畢業的
Then also did clinical
然後也做過臨床
Actually I'm interested in some biomedical stuff
其實我對一些生物醫學的東西
It's all old stuff
已經都是老掉牙的東西
Study something every day and keep improving
研究的東西每天日信約一直在進步
So I haven't attended school in more than ten years
所以我等於十幾年沒有在學校裡面上課
not that long
沒那麼久啦
Haven't attended school for many years
很多年沒有在學校上課
Then go back to school all of a sudden
那突然要回到學校裡面去
It's actually quite hard work
其實是還蠻辛苦的
Again in a person who doesn't understand much English
又是在一個英文聽不太懂的
then long gone is
然後很久去的是
because i used to
因為我以前
In our time, it was probably not bad to read and read.
我們那個年代大概讀啊看啊都還不錯
Can't hear well
聽不太行
I can't write well
寫也不太行
So I was afraid that when I first met a professor in the United States, I would
所以為了怕我第一次去見美國的教授的時候會
hard to hear
聽不清
i don't know what he's talking about
我不知道他在講什麼
He doesn't know what I'm talking about
他也不知道我在講什麼
So I took my wife to be an interpreter like this
所以我是帶我太太去當翻譯這樣子
I still have a clear impression
我印象還很清楚
But we are pushing our three month old
但是我們是推著我們三個月大的
we are called boss
我們叫老大
Then take my wife to be an interpreter like this
然後帶著我太太去當翻譯這樣子
to avoid
才避免
Difficulties in communication start like this
溝通上的困難這樣開始
Then
然後
You still have to take a lot of courses in the first year
第一年還是要修很多修一些課
to fix something like
要修一些像
Like the five-character class in the Department of Electrical Engineering
像電機系五字頭的課
It's the kind of master's degree in electrical engineering.
就是那種電機系的碩士
Courses currently being taken in doctoral programs
博士班在修的課
I'm ashamed to tell you
很慚愧跟各位說
Especially the architectural degree here
特別是建築學歷在這邊
When I was in my PhD class last year
我去年博士班的時候
I even forgot about the ohm force
我連那個歐姆定力我都忘記了
But he went to take the five-character course in the Department of Electrical Engineering
但是他去修那個電機系五字頭的課
So it's a big challenge
所以其實是滿大的挑戰
Generally business engineering
一般就是生意工程
Even you have to learn biology
就是你生物也要學
Engineering also needs to be learned
工程也要學
So take a bunch of classes
所以要修一堆課
Take forty or fifty students
修四五十個學生
Then you have to test a lot of things
然後要考一堆事
before graduation
然後才能畢業
But after a few years
不過經過我幾年
Seventy to eighty hours a week
每個禮拜七十到八十個小時
time work
時間式的工作
twenty to
每天二十個到
Twenty to thirty hours a week
每個禮拜二十個到三十個小時
results that can be lost at home
在家裡面可以輸的結果
i'm lucky
我還滿幸運的
I graduated in four years and two months
我四年兩個月畢業的
Then I want to thank my vice
然後我要很謝謝我的vice
my colleagues
我的colleague
And my wife and my wife's mother look like this
還有我太太跟我太太的媽媽這樣子
Because of our years in Seattle
因為我們在西雅圖那幾年
he went eight times
他去了八次
we have weight
我們一有重
Anyway, if there is weight, pull him to help
反正有重量就把他拉去幫忙
and our aunt
還有我們的阿姨
what does my doctoral class do
我的博士班做什麼呢
because my teacher is
因為我的老師是
There are many stories about my teacher
我的老師的故事有很多
can speak for two hours
可以講兩個小時
but basically
不過基本上
He's also a Harper's surgeon
他也是一個哈伯的外科醫師
But he spends 70% of his time doing research
但是他花了70%的時間都在做研究
So he is actually at the University of Washington, which is independent in West Asia
所以他事實上是在西亞獨的華盛頓大學
He established the entire surgical research system
他把整個外科的研究系統建立起來
At the time this was very rare
在當時這個是非常少的
To this day, few surgeons can do this
到今天還是很少外科醫生可以這樣子做
he uses a
他利用一個
Use the lungs
利用肺肺
A model of this kind of collar from part of the lungs
來部分肺肺的這種領長類的model
to experiment
來做實驗
what experiment
做什麼實驗呢
Because we do bypass surgery for artificial blood vessels
因為我們做人工血管的繞道手術
or a stent for blood vessels
或者是做血管的支架
The problem that will be encountered is the blood vessel
都會遭遇到的問題就是血管
Although you opened it up
你雖然把它打通了
But you artificial things
可是你這些人工的東西
foreign body reaction
會引發外異物性的反應
so it's like saying your hand was cut with a knife
所以它就好像說你的手被刀子割到
it will heal in the wound
它會在傷口會浴合
But it heals the wound too much
可是它浴合傷口浴合過頭
So some weird scars
所以長一些很奇怪的疤痕
artificial blood vessel
人工血管跟人工
artificial stent placed in blood vessel
人工支架放到血管裡面去
These tissues will also grow
也是一樣會長出這些組織
Finally, the blood vessel is blocked again
最後就把血管又把它堵起來
I came to find out
我來發現說
if you can increase
如果你可以增加
When the blood flow of this artificial blood vessel
這個人工血管的血流量的時候
then you can
那你就可以
grow this out
把這個已經長出來了
These tissues inside the artificial blood vessel
在人工血管裡面的這些組織
it can be retracted again
可以讓它再縮回去
So again blood flow can be suggested
所以又重新可以建議血流
how to do this
那怎麼去做這種
How can this make the blood flow in the blood vessels faster?
怎麼這樣可以讓血管裡面的血流速變快呢
For example, our person
比如說我們這個人的
This is boiling is this part
這是沸沸是本部
its aorta to the arteries of both feet
它的主動脈到兩隻腳的動脈
We connect its two artificial blood vessels
我們把它兩根人工血管接起來
tie it in the middle
中間再把它綁起來
So the blood can only go this way
所以血液只能從這邊走
after those two months
那兩個月之後
It will grow a lot of intima tissue
它就會長很多的內膜組織
At this time, if we are in a remote place
這個時候我們如果在遠端的地方
Connect its arteries and veins
把它動脈跟靜脈接起來
We all know that normally our arteries go to the vascular
大家知道正常我們動脈要到維血管
Will it reach the vein?
才會到靜脈嘛
Then the way I use surgery now
那我現在利用手術的方式
connect it directly
直接把它接起來
You can let the blood run here and run straight over
就可以讓血流跑這裡直接跑過去
it's like saying
這就好像說
Originally, there were only three lanes on one side of the expressway.
高速公路本來一邊只有三線道
You suddenly turn it into a six-lane lane
你突然把它開變成一邊六線道
The draw will definitely speed up
抽數一定會加快
What about the blood flow speeding up?
那這血流數加快的同時呢
It will make the growing tissue shrink again
就會讓長出來的這個組織再縮小
retracted again
再縮回去了
then you tie this side up
那你把這邊綁起來
it grows again
它又長出來了
So its organization is actually scalable.
所以它這個組織其實是可以伸縮的
ok now here comes the problem
好 那現在問題來了
If there is a patient today
如果說今天有一個病人
His artificial blood vessel is about to become blocked.
他的人工血管快要被堵住了
You say sorry to him
你跟他說 對不起喔
I let you open one
我讓你來腳開一個
Open a Tokyo Mailou tube surgery
開一個東京脈樓管的手術
I can make you shrink back
我就可以讓你這個縮回去
Does the patient want you to do it?
病人要不要讓你做
Of course not
當然不要啊
probably no one would
大概沒有人會這樣子
So all we have to do is say
所以我們要做的就是說
if i could know say
如果我可以知道說
This increase in blood flow
這個血流數所增加
Why do these tissues grow
為什麼會讓這些長出來的組織
retracted words
縮回去的話
then i can know
那我就可以有知道說
What are the things that I can design drugs for?
哪些東西是可以我來設計藥物
to do something similar
來做到類似的作用
Then we can use drugs
那我們就可以用藥物的方式
to simulate the effect of this increased blood flow
來模擬這個血流增加的作用
We often do research in this way
我們做研究常常都是用這樣的方式
It's us who bully animals
就是我們就是欺負動物
bully them and do some
欺負他們 然後做一些
things that happened that they shouldn't have
他們本來不應該有的發生的事情
learn from it
從中裡面去學習到
Thanks also to their students
也謝謝他們的學生
So we can learn to say
所以我們就可以學習到說
Maybe how can we diagnose a disease earlier
也許我們可以怎麼樣可以更早的去診斷一個疾病
how to get better treatment
怎麼樣可以去做更好的治療
Then after finishing his Ph.D., he went to Doctorate to be a postdoctoral fellow.
那念完博士之後就跑到博士頓去做博士後
We have been to Doctorston
大家去過博士頓
You can also see this is the view of Temi
也可以看到這個都是特米的景色
Halwegen MIT looks like this
哈爾維根MIT這樣子
But for us
不過對我們來講
In fact, it is this thing that affects us the most.
其實影響我們最大的是這個東西
i hope there are not too many
我希望這裡不要有太多
yangjid fans
楊吉德球迷
me and my wife
我跟我太太
because the year we went
因為我們去的那一年
Year 2003
2003年
end of 2003
2003年底
year 2004
2004年
All year 2004
一整年2004年
He just breaks that Bamber's Cube
他就打破那個Bamber's Cube
is the curse
就是魔咒
Won another world championship after 1984
84年以後又拿了一次世界冠軍
so i appreciate him
所以我很感激他
So my wife and I decided
所以我跟我太太決定
We're going to be Saffron fans for life
我們終身要變成紅花隊的球迷
So when I got back, I joked
所以回來以後就開玩笑說
if you are a yangjid fan
如果是楊吉德球迷
better not come into my office like this
最好不要進我的辦公室這樣
But didn't Wang Jianming go to Yangji later?
不過後來王建銘不是到楊吉去嗎
That's right, when Wang Jianming pitches the ball
就是好 那王建銘投球的時候
yangji can win
楊吉可以贏
When Wang Jianming is not pitching
王建銘不投球的時候
better not win
最好不要贏
From the time of postdoctoral
那從在博士後的時候
Start to learn how to make stem cells
就開始去學習怎麼去做幹細胞
How to make these nanotechnology
怎麼去做這些奈米的科技
That's because I came back later
那因為我後續回來
This year is the tenth year in Taiwan
台灣到現在今年是第十年
Our time is more than nine years
我們時間是已經九年多了
What I have done in the tenth year is related to this context.
這第十年做的都是跟這個脈絡有關係的
So I'll just go straight to what we're doing in this space
所以我就直接介紹我們在這個領域所做的
good
好
Before we start talking about regeneration
那在開始講心機再生之前
I would like to introduce a very interesting research
我想先介紹一個很有趣的研究
I like to share with you
我很喜歡跟大家分享
This is a cross-border cooperation between the United States and Egypt
這是一個美國跟埃及跨國的合作
what to do
做什麼呢
Here is the mummy of an Egyptian 3,000 years ago
這邊是一個三千年前埃及人的木乃伊
It's a princess mummy
這是一個公主的木乃伊
get the mummy out
那把木乃伊拿出來
Whole-body computed tomography scan
利用全身的電腦斷層掃描
that can be seen very white
那可以看到很白色
brighter ones
比較亮的這些
It's where the arteriosclerosis is
都是它的動脈硬化的位置
The one on the right is a modern Egyptian
右邊這個是一個現代的埃及人
It's the same as doing a full-body computerized tomography examination.
一樣把它做全身的電腦斷層的檢查
same white as this
一樣白色的這個
They all represent places where arteriosclerosis is covered
都是代表了動脈硬化蓋化的地方
You can see that
各位可以看到說
From the aorta of our heart, the spectator artery, to
從我們的心臟主動脈 觀眾動脈到
From the aorta in our abdomen to the two feet these branches
我們的腹部的主動脈到兩隻腳這些分支
In fact, the gap of three thousand years
其實三千年的差距
did not cause much change in the disease of arteriosclerosis
並沒有對動脈硬化的疾病造成多大的改變
That is to say, even after three thousand years of evolution
也就是說即使經過了三千年的演化
The disease is still
這個疾病其實還在
i joked
我開玩笑說
If our air continues to deteriorate like it has these days
如果我們的空氣像這幾天這樣繼續惡化下去
Can human beings live on the earth for another 3,000 years?
人類能不能在地球再活三千年
may be a problem
可能是一個問題
but if you can
但假如可以的話
After 3000 years, we will take people out to make
三千年後我們再把人拿出來做
Whole body computerized tomography scan
全身電腦斷層的掃描
maybe still like this
可能還是這個樣子
In other words, arteriosclerosis is actually an ancient disease.
也就是說動脈硬化其實是一個古老的疾病
It's not like this today because everyone eats well
不是今天因為大家吃得好才變這樣子的
OK
OK
So what's the problem with hardening?
那動蠻硬化會產生什麼問題呢?
If this blood vessel hardens, it will become narrower and narrower
如果這個血管動蠻硬化它會越來越狹窄
The blood cannot run through, or even be blocked.
血就跑不過去 甚至被堵住
If we block our brains, we will have a stroke
那堵到我們的大腦就變中風
Myocardial infarction
堵到心臟就是心肌梗塞
If the feet are blocked, the feet will turn black
堵到腳 腳就會黑掉
If the intestines are blocked, the intestines will turn black
堵到腸子 腸子就會黑掉
OK
OK
What happens in the heart is what we call a myocardial infarction
那在心臟會產生的就是我們所說的心肌梗塞
Then I often remind my friends
那我常常要提醒我周遭的朋友們
In Taiwan we are all cultural cancer
在台灣我們都是文癌設辯
We all know that cancer is the number one cause of death in Taiwan
大家知道癌症是台灣排名第一的死因
we all know that
這我們都知道
But that's all cancers added up
可是那是所有癌症全部加起來的
If we look at individual organs
如果我們以個別器官來看的話
The heart is still the single organ that kills the most people in the country
心臟還是奪走最多國人生命的一個單一器官
Please keep this in mind for a chance to encourage heart research like this
請大家記住這一點有機會多鼓勵一下心臟的研究這樣
Then if it is because of the main color of the arteries
那如果因為觀將動脈主色之後
cause myocardial necrosis
會造成心肌的壞死
Our heart itself doesn't regenerate very well
我們的心臟本身它的再生能力不太好
Everyone may know this
這個可能大家都知道
Necrotic myocardium will slowly fibrosis
壞死的心肌它慢慢就會纖維化
It will be like the gray and white place here
就會像這邊灰白色的位置
This red one is our special dyeing
這紅色的是我們利用特殊的染色
叫Tricon Staining
叫Tricon Staining
live cardiac tissue
可以把活的心肌的組織
still dyed red
還是染成紅色
fibrotic, hardened
已經纖維化已經硬掉的
The myocardium without function will turn grayish white
沒有功能的這個心肌它就會變成灰白色
You can see that I used another cartoon instead
各位可以看到我用另外一個卡通圖來代替
That is to say, the position of myocardial necrosis
也就是說心肌梗色壞死的這個位置
it gradually becomes thinner
它慢慢會變得比較薄
become thinner
變得比較薄
But our hearts keep saying
可是我們的心臟一直在說說
The heart is the hardest working organ in our body
心臟是我們人體裡面工作最勤奮的器官
From when you were inside your mother's womb
從你在媽媽肚子裡面的時候
it starts jumping
它就開始跳
ten weeks it started jumping
十個禮拜它就開始跳
skip till you are born skip till you grow up
跳到你出生跳到你長大
Jump to you one day getting old enough to go away
跳到你有一天年紀越來越大到走掉
it keeps jumping
它一直都在跳
jumping all the time
隨時都在跳
can't stop
不能停下來
In the process of shrinking and jumping
在一直收縮一直跳的過程當中
it will get thinner for this
它會對這個變得比較薄
Compare
比較
Relatively less powerful
比較沒有那麼大的機界力的
That mind-blowing pair creates pressure
那個心事幣對造成壓力
so it pushes it
所以它會推擠它
let it bash out
讓它抨出去
If you slam it, it will pull the more normal scheming
那抨出去就會去拉扯本來比較正常的心機
cause secondary damage
會造成二次傷害
So this heart will slowly grow bigger and bigger
所以這個心臟慢慢就會越來越大
getting bigger and bigger
越來越脹越大
become not only bigger but also thinner
變得不僅越大而且越來越薄
So the heart can contract like this
所以本來心臟是可以這樣子收縮的
That's because of partial heart attack
那因為局部的心機梗色
one day it will be like this
有一天它會變成這樣子
Shrinkage agent is weak
收縮劑沒有力
Books and chapters have no strength
書章也沒有力
So this is actually true of one of our patient's chest s-lights
所以這實際上是真的是我們一個病人的胸部S光
Everyone has had chest s-rays
各位都照過胸部S光
The shaded part of white is the patient's heart
白色的這個陰影的部分就是這個病人的心臟
If you have any impression, remember
各位如果有印象還記得
Go back and compare the S light you made
你回去比較一下自己所造的S光
You know your heart is probably like this
你就知道你的心臟大概只有這樣子而已
For this patient, we usually calculate the ratio of chest enlargement and heart reduction
這個病人我們通常會算這個胸擴心臟的削鬥的比例
This patient has probably reached 85% to almost 90%
這個病人大概已經到了85%到快90%
We normal people are usually only about 50%
我們正常人通常都是只有50%左右而已
So when a heart is so dirty
所以當一個心臟已經臟到這麼大的時候
he can only be like this
他只能這樣子
So you can imagine if this patient can go for a jog
所以各位可以想像這個病人有沒有辦法去慢跑
is there a way to go up and down the stairs
有沒有辦法去上下樓梯
There's not even a way he can just lie on the bed and ship
甚至都沒辦法他只能躺在床上船
even if he started with a localized heart problem
即使他一開始的時候只是局部的心臟的問題
How can we help such a patient?
那這樣的病人我們要怎麼去幫助他呢
Do you want to guess what there is a thing over here?
要不要猜猜看這邊有一顆東西是什麼
This is called a war machine
這個叫去戰器
difibrator
difibrator
Because this patient is normally like this
因為這個病人他本來正常是這樣子
he's become like this now
他現在變成是這樣子
sometimes he's like this
有的時候他就會這樣子
what to do at this time
這個時候要做什麼
Hurry up pad
趕快墊
or to press
或者要壓
to do CPR
要做CPR
Otherwise the patient will rest immediately
要不然這個病人馬上就休息
please remember
請大家記住一點
If you encounter such a situation around you
如果你萬一在你周遭遇到這樣的狀況
someone exposed
有人露倒
you feel his pulse in the neck
你摸他的頸部的脈搏
don't touch your hands touch your neck
不要摸手 手摸頸部
The neck is the most clearly palpable
頸部是最清楚摸得到的
if you can't feel your pulse
如果你摸不到脈搏
don't do anything
什麼事情都不要做
Don't go to the Human Services Association, don't rush him
也不要去人工務協 不要去催他
direct pressure
直接壓
it's ok
就可以了
but first thing
但是第一件事情
What is CPR first thing
CPR第一件事情是什麼
right
對
Call help
Call help
hurry up
趕快
Hurry up and call 119
趕快打119
call for help
趕快叫人幫忙
Not mouth to mouth or pressure
不是去口對口也不是去壓
neither
都不是
The first thing in CPR is called call help
CPR第一件事情叫做call help
find someone to help
找人來幫忙
then press
然後就壓
The latest concept
現在最新的概念
you don't need artificial respiration
你不需要去人工呼吸
Just keep pressing, pressing, pressing
就是一直壓壓壓壓壓壓
Just push until someone comes to help.
壓到有人來幫忙就是了
don't mess with electricity
也不要亂電
If you can feel his pulse
你如果摸得到他的脈搏
you don't need electricity
你就不要電
Because he was still dancing normally
因為他本來還是正常在跳
He might be finished after being shocked by you.
被你這一電他可能就完了
so don't mess with electricity
所以不要亂電
I will remind you every time
我每次都會提醒
Because our children's elementary school used to be
因為以前我們小朋友的小學
The principal of the primary school asked me
小學的校長問我說
Everything needs to be placed where the electrical appliances should be placed.
全部都要放那個電器去要放哪裡
sometimes it's better not to let go
有時候最好不要放
It's actually dangerous
其實是有危險的
Such patients we
那這樣的病人我們
Usually that's the way to help him
通常就是這個辦法來幫助他就是
heart transplant
心臟移植
But we don't have that many hearts to transplant
不過我們沒有那麼多心臟可以來做移植
especially in taiwan
特別在台灣
so
所以
Even today, there are one hundred patients waiting for patients with heart disease at National Taiwan University Hospital every day.
即使到今天每天在台大醫院都有一百個病人在等待患心
come help
來救命
Every day, 150 people in Taiwan are waiting for heart surgery to save their lives
全台灣每天有150個人在等待患心手術來救命
We don't have that many hearts to suffer from
我們沒有那麼多心臟可以患
But these patients are still poor
可是這些病人還是很可憐
Don't you think he has only one patient and he's affecting the whole family
你不要以為他只有一個病人他影響到是整個家庭
When there are a hundred families with this patient saying he affects a community or even a
當有一百個家庭都有這樣的病人說他影響到是一個社區甚至是一個
nation
國家
it's actually serious
這實際上是很嚴重的事情
So what we want to be able to do is is there a way
所以我們希望能夠做的是有沒有辦法
we can
我們可以
I just said
我剛有說嘛
After 3,000 years, people may still have sexual arousal
在三千年之後人可能還是會產生性激感社
we knew he would be like this
我們知道他會這樣子
But we hope he doesn't change like this
可是我們希望他不要變這樣子
or at least not like this
或者至少不要變這樣子
No patient like this will come in for a new operation
不會有這樣子的病人要來做換新的手術
How to do it
怎麼做
There may be several ways
可能有這幾種方式
First
第一個
Let's protect the heart muscle early
我們早期來做心肌的保護
because
因為
After the blood vessel is blocked
血管一堵住之後
Myocardial hypoxia-ischemia
在馬上就會造成心肌缺氧缺血
Myocardial necrosis may occur immediately
馬上就可能會心肌壞死
Taiwan's medical system is actually very good.
那台灣的醫療系統其實非常好
Don't worry about whether the country's finances can afford it
先不要管說國家財政能不能負擔
It's really one of our biggest
這真的是我們最大的一個
one
一個
The people's welfare, I'm honest
人民的福利啦我老實講
Of course some people have to be sacrificed
當然要犧牲一些人
Only by sacrificing some talents can we say that Taiwan's medical quality is good, convenient and cheap
犧牲一些人才有辦法說台灣的醫療品質又好又方便又便宜
People must be sacrificed, otherwise there is no such good thing in the world
一定要人犧牲嘛不然哪有天下哪有這麼好的事情
Sacrificial groups include
犧牲的族群就包括
Standing in front of this one like this
站在最前面這一位這樣
ignore him
不管他
now in taiwan
現在在台灣
All we can do is patients with myocardial infarction
我們可以做得到的只要是有心肌梗塞的病人
sent to emergency room
送到急診
after
之後
He was diagnosed with a myocardial infarction, and his blood vessels must be opened within 90 minutes.
確診他有心肌梗塞在90分鐘之內要趕快把他的血管打通
you can hit
你可以打
Thrombotropic Drugs
容血栓的藥物
You can also go straight to a new catheter
也可以直接去做新導管
You can put the bracket
放支架都可以
but within 90 minutes
但是就是90分鐘之內
It is necessary to complete this operation
就要把它完成這個手術
this process
這個過程
Why? Because after a myocardial infarction
為什麼?因為心肌梗塞之後
Only 4 hours to 6 hours
只有4個小時到6個小時的時間
It can be used to protect the heart muscle
可以來做心肌的保護
beyond this time
超過這個時間
What I'm doing may be superfluous
在做的可能都是多餘的
it doesn't help much
就沒有太大的幫助
So this is to protect the heart muscle early
所以這個是要早期做心肌的保護
OK
OK
the second one
那第二個
if we...
如果我們...
because it is an ischemic
因為它是一個缺血性
hypoxia problem
缺氧的問題
blood vessel problem
血管出問題的
So if we can do therapeutic
所以我們如果能夠做治療性的
increase its blood vessels
增加它的血管
grow more blood vessels
長出更多的血管
Of course it will help the function of the heart
當然對心臟的功能會有幫助
The third
第三個
you know its dead part
你知道它壞死的部分
will eventually become thinner and thinner
最後會變得越來越薄
If you can punch it in and inject some material
你如果可以打進去注射一些材料
some business material
一些生意的材料
or drugs
或者是藥物
can make this mind coin
可以讓這個心事幣
Even if it is necrotic it will not thin
即使壞死它不會變薄
Then it can maintain its strength
那它就可以維持它那個強度
so the heart can sustain it to continue the surgery
所以心臟就可以維持它繼續的手術
won't be beaten
就不會被撐打
then if it has thinned
那如果它已經變薄了
but not too big
但是還沒有變得很大
then we can do...
那我們可以做...
is to make a whole heart muscle
就是做出整塊的心肌
It's like we're mending clothes
就好像我們在補衣服這樣子
patch it to the outside of the heart
把它補到心臟的外面
Let it contract with the heart
讓它可以跟著心臟一起收縮
You guys think I'm talking about cartoons
各位覺得好像我在講卡通這樣子
Taiwanese called official card
台語叫做公辦卡
In fact, all these are being done
其實這些都有在做
We are all doing it
我們身世都有在做
Many people all over the world are doing
全世界很多人也都在做
I will take some examples today
我今天會拿一些例子來
Everyone for reference
各位做參考
The other one is actually our favorite
另外一個其實是我們最喜歡的
This is our unique trick
這個是我們的獨門絕招
Although we were the first to do
雖然我們是最早開始做
prove this thing
證明這件事情
That is to say, it is supplementing the five types of animals
也就是說在補五類動物
Including mice, including humans, of course
包括老鼠 包括人當然
In fact, after our heart muscle is damaged
其實在我們心肌受損之後
It triggers in our body
它會引發我們身體裡面
endogenous stem cells
有一群內生性的幹細胞
it goes to where this damaged heart muscle
它會跑到這個受損的心肌的地方
to regenerate
去做再生
it grows some cardiomyocytes
它會長出一些心肌細胞
but few
但是數目很少
So however we are the first to prove that
所以不過我們是第一個證明說
really have this thing
真的有這件事情
Of course there's one thing that's going to happen on Earth
當然地球上有一件事情會發生
just not enough
只是不夠
then once you understand it
那你一旦了解它
you can find ways to stimulate
你就可以想辦法去刺激
make it more
讓它更多
if this never happened
如果這件事情根本就不會發生
you have to make something out of nothing
你要無中生有
probably more difficult
大概就比較困難
So all we have to do is
所以我們要做的就是
how to find this
怎麼樣去找到這個
Where are the endogenous stem cells?
內生性的幹細胞到底在哪裡
how it is activated
它怎麼被啟動
is there a way to take a medicine
有沒有辦法吃一顆藥
can make this regenerative ability stronger
就可以讓這個再生的能力更強
Ours is actually our favorite
我們這個其實是我們最喜歡的
its spontaneous endogeneity
它的自發性的內生性
original ability to regenerate
原來就有的再生的能力
Okay, then I will mainly introduce to you today.
好 那我今天主要跟各位介紹
three things
三個東西
The first is our endogenous stem cells
第一個就是我們內生性的幹細胞
how to regenerate heart muscle
怎麼樣去再生心肌
The second one is to tell you
第二個要跟各位講
How can we use tissue engineering
我們怎麼樣利用組織工程
Combining biomedicine and engineering
就結合生物 醫學 跟工程
Three ways to help the heart repair and regenerate
三個方式來幫助心臟的修復跟再生
the third one
那第三個
recent news
最近新聞鬧的
The news is a little louder
新聞吵得比較大一點點的就是
How do we use wearing stem cells
我們怎麼樣利用佩戴幹細胞
or induced pluripotent stem cells
或者是誘導性多全能幹細胞
These early stem cells come from
這些早期的乾細胞來
cardiomyocytes
分化成為心肌細胞
and then let it become mature cardiomyocytes
然後讓它變成成熟的心肌細胞
We can use it for drug picking
我們可以拿它來做藥物採選
able to be used for treatment
能夠拿來做治療所用的
I'll start with the endogenous relationship package
我就從內生性幹系包開始
everyone look at this
各位看這個
I think most people may not understand
我想大部分人可能都看不懂
Even explaining to the professor three times in medicine
即使在醫學裡面跟教授解釋三次
He doesn't necessarily know how to listen and tell the truth
他也不一定聽得懂得說實話
so i just jump over
所以我就是跳過去
But I tell you, please believe me
但是我跟 請各位相信我這樣子
Now that you're here, you just have to trust me
你既然來了就只好相信我了
We really have a group of endogenous relationship packages in us
我們身裡面真的有一群內生性的幹系包
Can go to regenerate scheming
可以去再生心機
what did we do
我們做了什麼呢
we found that
我們發現說
This is of course a mouse
這個當然是老鼠
We all love using mice for animal models
我們都喜歡用老鼠來做動物模式
Not because mice are easy to bully
不是因為老鼠好欺負
It means that the mouse is one of the five types of animals
而是說老鼠他是卜五類動物
Then we make transgenic mice
然後我們做基因轉植鼠
A lot of people around the world do it and we do it too
在全世界很多人做我們也做
So the transgenic mouse
所以基因轉植鼠
Transgenic mice are easier to make
基因轉植鼠比較容易做
So let's take it and make our animal model
所以我們拿它來做我們一個動物模式
If in mice we can see good results
如果在老鼠我們可以看到好的結果
then we'll jump up
那我們就會往上跳
Larger animals even become humans
大一點的動物甚至做人
So the mouse is actually more
所以老鼠其實是更
that contributed a lot
那貢獻很大的
Of course I'm talking about rats, experimental animals.
當然我講的是實驗動物的老鼠
It's not the rats that come and go in your house.
不是你家裡面那片專來專去的老鼠
not the same
不太一樣
We use a more complex gene rotor mouse model
我們利用一個比較複雜的基因轉子鼠的model
first time to prove that
第一次去證明說
After myocardial infarction in mice
在老鼠心肌梗式之後
Parts with necrosis and parts without necrosis
壞死的部分跟沒有壞死的部分
We call this the middle ground
我們這個叫做中間地帶
It will be a place where the stem cells are most active
它會有是一個幹細胞最活躍的地方
15% of stem cells grow new heart muscle
有15%的幹細胞會長出新的心肌
to fix it
來修補它
Then you will think that 15% is a lot.
那各位會覺得15%很多啊
yeah 15% is a lot
是啊 15%是很多
But it's only around the necrosis
不過它只有在壞死的周圍
that small circle around
那一圈很小的周圍
That lap is 15%
那一圈才是15%
Going outside leaves only 5%, 7% or even nothing
到外面去就只剩下5% 7%甚至沒有
So it's definitely not enough for the whole heart
所以對整個心臟來講是絕對不夠的
So we want to say how can we
因此我們要想說我們怎麼樣可以
Find out where these endogenous stem cells come from
找到這些內生性的幹細胞從哪裡來的
then we can stimulate it
那我們就可以去刺激它
Let it generate more new muscle regeneration
讓它產生更多的新肌再生
Then this study started when I was waiting for Boss
那這個study從我以前在Boss等時候開始做
and then later
然後後來是
two PhD students
兩個博士班的學生
Welcome Zhang and American side Jasmin
迎張跟美方Jasmin
they all graduated
他們都畢業了
Jasmin is currently working as a postdoctoral fellow in Germany
Jasmin現在在德國做博士後
Welcome to Zhang Zai, former president of the State Council
迎張在國務院前院長
Experimenters I can know as postdoctoral fellows
我可以認識的實驗師做博士後
They did the first study
他們做了第一個study
Just do this study
就做一個這個study
that is
就是
After myocardial infarction in mice
在心肌梗塞老鼠之後
How does he have an endogenous dry bag to regenerate heart muscle
他怎麼樣會有內生性的幹性包來再生心肌
how long does he need
他需要多久的時間
what time is the most important
什麼時間也是最重要的
So we did a very simple experiment
所以我們就做了一個很簡單的實驗
After myocardial infarction in mice
在老鼠心肌梗塞之後的
Seven days Ten days Fourteen days Twenty-one days Twenty-eight days
七天 十天 十四天 二十一天 二十八天
Fifty-six days to eighty-four days to three months
五十六天 到八十四天 到三個月
Let's talk about this dry bag
來看看說這個幹性包
How to regenerate heart muscle
到底是怎麼樣去再生心肌的
Our original thought was
我們本來的想法是
a little every day a little every day
每天來一點 每天來一點
15% in the end
最後有15%
Surprisingly, it was found
結果很意外的發現
Actually not like this
其實沒有這樣子
seven days
七天的時候
There is a clear dry package that regenerates the myocardium
就有很明顯的幹性包會再生心肌
It's over in ten days
到十天就結束了
you've been waiting for no more
你在等在久都沒有更多的
Dry pack regenerates heart muscle
幹性包會再生心肌
This is actually an interesting result
這其實是一個很有趣的結果
What do you guys think of a picture like this
各位覺得說一張圖這樣子
That's seven days and ten days
就是這樣七天十天
But do you know how much time we spent on this picture
可是你知道這一張圖我們花了多少時間去做
Eighteen million five years to get this result
五年的時間一千八百萬才得到這個結果
I won't talk about the details anymore.
那細節我就不再說了
Then we found out that since it will be so soon
接下來我們發現說既然這麼快就會被
Stem cells are primed after cell suffocation
乾細胞就會在細胞梗酥之後被引發
So what is the signal and what mechanism to stimulate it?
那到底是什麼訊號什麼樣的機制去激發它
you will want to say
你就會想說
What happened to Xinji infarction
新濟梗塞發生什麼事情
What happened when your hand was cut with a knife?
你手被刀子割到發生什麼事情
What happens if your hand is cut with a knife?
手被刀子割到會怎麼樣
It hurts, of course it hurts
會痛啊 當然會痛
redness hot pain
紅 腫 熱 痛
The inflammatory reaction we are talking about is redness, swelling, heat, pain
我們講的發炎反應就是紅 腫 熱 痛
red why red
紅 為什麼會紅
Of course the first blood will be red
初血當然會紅
But if you have tissues in your body, you will dirty a lot of capillaries
不過你要組織在身會髒很多微血管
so it will be red
所以它會紅
why is it swollen
為什麼會腫
Because the blood vessel ruptures, the tissue will come out
因為血管破裂會組織會跑出來
If blood comes out, it will swell
血液跑出來會腫
it's hot why is it hot
會熱 為什麼會熱
because its partial like
因為它的局部喜歡
It can only be repaired, so it will be hot
它才能修復嘛 所以會熱
Why does it hurt?
為什麼會痛?
because of the pressure on the nerve
因為會壓迫到神經
or you release a lot of tissue
或者你釋放了很多的組織
it stimulates your peripheral nerves
它會刺激你的末梢神經
so you will hurt
所以你會痛
OK as long as the body is injured
OK 只要身體受傷受損
You will be red, hot, painful and inflamed
你就會紅腫熱痛就會發炎
Myocardial infarction too
心肌梗塞也一樣
So when we take medicine
所以當我們如果利用吃藥
to suppress your inflammatory response
去抑制你的發炎反應的時候
You won't be in pain, you won't be red, swollen and hot
你就不會痛 就不會紅腫熱痛
But you also suppress your relationship package
但是你也把你的幹系包給壓一住
It just won't come out, there's no heart muscle regeneration
它就不會出來了 就沒有心肌再生了
OK
OK
OK, so if we use
好 那如果我們用
you suppress the inflammatory response
你抑制發炎反應
Relationship package won't come out
幹系包就不出來
then if i stimulate it
那我如果刺激它
make it more inflammatory
讓它更多的發炎反應
Will more related packages come out?
會不會就有更多的幹系包跑出來
Really, but you have to stimulate the right
真的會 但是你要刺激對
you need to give the right medicine
你要給對的藥物
Giving the wrong medicine won't help
給錯的藥物就沒有用
Then we found that there is a prostaglandin E2
那我們發現有一個前列腺素E2
called PGE2
叫PGE2
It can stimulate more stem packs
它可以刺激讓更多的幹系包
can become cardiomyocytes
可以變成心肌細胞
From 15% to 20%
從15%變成20%
then next
那接下來
The problem is that we usually do mice
這個問題是我們通常做老鼠
It's all done with young mice
都是用年輕的老鼠去做
Because it's cheaper, faster, and simpler
因為比較便宜 比較快 比較簡單
But we know patients who say they will have a myocardial infarction
可是我們知道說會發生心肌梗塞的病人
In fact, they are relatively older
其實相對年紀都是比較大的
Although I also recently heard
雖然我最近也聽到
An 18-year-old had a myocardial infarction
有一個18歲的就產生心肌梗塞
It is true that age has declined
的確是年齡又以來下降
but generally speaking
不過一般來說
Most common myocardial infarction patients are older
最常見心肌梗塞病人還是年紀比較大的
Of course we have to use older ones for mice
老鼠我們當然也要用年紀比較大的去做
Surprisingly, we found that
那很意外的是我們發現說
older mice
年紀比較大的老鼠
It's normal after a myocardial infarction
它正常的情況之下心肌梗塞之後
Its stem cells will not regenerate heart muscle
它的幹系胞是不會去再生心肌的
But if you put our PGE2
可是你如果把我們PGE2
The limit of this potential can be punched in
這個潛力的限數再打進去
It can restore the same ability as when it was young
它就可以恢復跟年輕時候差不多的能力
15% of myocardium's ability to regenerate
15%的心肌再生的能力
This experiment is actually very important
這個實驗其實很重要
British all over the world
全世界的英國的
The President of the New University Association came to Taiwan to give a speech
新大學會的President來臺灣演講
He also helped us publicize that this great strength is really important.
還幫我們宣傳說這個大力真的很重要
why is it important
為什麼重要
because he told us
因為他告訴我們
You worry that when people are getting older and older
你會擔心說人越來年紀越來越大的時候
Are the stem cells gone?
是不是幹細胞就沒有了
Or stem cells don't work
或者是幹細胞就沒有作用的
It looks like this
紮看之下好像是這樣子
But after stimulating us with drugs
可是給我們藥物刺激之後
In fact, stem cells still work
其實幹細胞還是會作用的
This represents two meanings
這代表了兩個意義
The first one even though older
第一個 即使年紀比較大
Stem cells are still there
幹細胞還是存在的
there is still hope
還是有希望的
It's not that when you get older
不是年紀大就沒有了
it's still there
它還是在的
But it may be affected by some volitional factor
可是它可能被一些意志的因子
hold it down
把它壓一住
Make these stem cells useless
讓這些幹細胞沒辦法作用
So if you can unravel the mystery
所以你如果能夠揭開神秘的面紗
Allow stem cells to regain their ability
讓幹細胞可以重新恢復它的能力
Then we can regenerate the new machine
那我們就可以再生新機
PG-2 is one of those that can do such a job
PG-2是其中一個可以做這樣的一個工作的
PG-2 is a drug that mainly removes
PG-2這個藥物主要就是會移除掉
factor of our aging
我們老化的因子
One of them is called TGF-Fatalone
其中一個叫TGF-Fatalone
Pressure-free is not very familiar with these
免壓是不太熟悉這些
it doesn't matter you know
沒有關係 你就知道
Anyway, there are many genes
反正基因有很多
this is one of the genes
這是其中一個基因
So PG-2 Treatment can
所以PG-2的Treatment可以
Beta this Cinema of TG in the aging heart
讓老化的心臟裡面的TG的β這個Cinema
hold it down
把它壓一住
So the lid cell can regain its ability to regenerate
所以蓋細胞就可以重新再恢復它再生的能力
So if we directly give
所以我們如果直接給
This drug that inhibits the beta of TG
抑制TG的β的這個藥物
we can restore some degree of
我們就可以恢復一定程度的
Scheming regenerated in the old you mouse
心機再生在老你的老鼠
So, if there are friends from the pharmacy here,
所以各位如果在場有藥場的朋友
you will know
你就會知道說
There are at least two things that can be developed
至少有兩個東西可以去開發
Drugs for Cardiac Regeneration
心機再生的藥物
One is called Pg2
一個叫Pg2
One called TGβ1
一個叫TGβ1
Right, that is it
對 就是這樣
The next question is
下一個問題就是
Where did these stem cells come from?
那這些幹細胞從哪裡來的
Most of the stem cells are actually in the heart
大部分的幹細胞其實是在心臟裡面
from the heart
從心臟
It wouldn't move
本來它都不會動
then you stimulate it
那你刺激它
it will start to work
它就會開始出來工作
But there is one thing everyone agrees on
可是有一個 這個大家都同意
But there is one thing that everyone has been controversial about.
可是有一個大家一直有爭議性的就是
Tonic in the bone marrow
骨髓裡面到補
or blood circulation
或者血液循環裡面
Are there any stem cells that can regenerate the brain?
到底有沒有幹細胞會去再生心機
we are very clear that
我們非常清楚的是
after myocardial infarction
心機梗色之後
It's the same with people
在人也是這樣子
you are going to mend
你要去修補
repair your heart muscle
修復你的心肌
You will be in the blood circulation from the bone marrow
你會從骨髓在血液循環裡面
There will be a lot of stem cells will come out
會有很多幹細胞會跑出來
Run to the heart to grow new blood vessels
跑到心臟去長出新的血管
turn into new cells to repair
變成新的細胞來修復
we already know this
這個我們早就知道了
But these bone marrow or blood circulation cells
可是這些骨髓或者是血液循環的細胞
Can it become new cardiomyocytes?
到底能不能變成新的心肌細胞
everyone speaks differently
每個人講的都不一樣
so we engage our gene transfer agency
所以我們接合我們基因轉職署
And let's bully the mice again
還有讓又欺負老鼠
Seal two mice together
把兩隻老鼠封在一起
so that his blood can be exchanged
讓他的血液可以去做交換
so we can study his genes
這樣我們就可以研究他的基因
so our first
所以我們第一次
It is also the first time to prove that
也是第一次證明說
In fact, the blood circulation
其實血液循環裡面
There is still a population of stem cells after myocardial infarction
還是有一群幹細胞在心肌梗塞之後
Not only does he go to the heart to help with repairs
他不僅會跑到心臟去幫忙做修復
He will even turn directly into cardiomyocytes
他甚至會直接變成心肌細胞
This is an important contribution of our study
這是我們這個研究比較重要的貢獻
good
好
Another study is
另外一個study是
is there any other way
有沒有另外別的辦法
In addition to drug stimulation
除了給藥物刺激以外
If I grow more blood vessels
我如果長出更多的血管
Would it also help endogenous myocardial regeneration
是不是也會幫助內生性的心肌再生
When all your fields are barren
當你一片都是荒蕪的田地的時候
it's hard for you to grow
你很難長出
grow crops
長出農作物
But if you open several channels
但是你如果開了幾條渠道
can irrigate
可以灌溉
after water can go in
水可以進去之後
you may grow new crops
你就有可能長出新的農作
Xinzang is also like this
新藏也是這樣子
So in another study
所以在另外一個study
This is my other one
這個是我另外一個
this is my first PhD student
這是我第一個博士班的學生
Later, he also stayed in the laboratory as a postdoctoral fellow.
後來也留在實驗室做博士後
Now working as a postdoctoral fellow at Harvard
現在在Harvard做博士後
Previous year at MIT
前一年在MIT
In the next year at Harvard like this
後一年在Harvard這樣
It is the first student in my lab
它是我實驗室第一個學生
everyone jokes
大家都開玩笑說
Usually there is a
通常有一個叫做
The first student call is always the best
第一個學生通話都是最好的
it's that kind
它就是那種
Anyway, everyone can't get the award
反正大家都拿不到的獎
the whole world for example
全世界譬如說
young student scientist
年輕的學生科學家
There are 10 bonuses that can be obtained
能夠拿到的獎金有10個
The only one in Asia is him
亞洲唯一一個就是他
Has won this award three times
已經拿過三次這種獎
very good student
非常好的學生
One of the studies is
其中一個study就是
we found that
我們發現說
If we use another rice-resistant glue
如果我們再利用一個耐米的水膠
combined with a growth factor
結合一個生長因子
When more blood vessels can grow
可以長出更多的血管的時候
Whether it is in Dashu or in pigs
不管是在大數或者是在豬
We can all grow more blood vessels
我們都可以長出更多的血管
and arterial blood vessels
而且是動脈的血管
Not capillaries, but arterial blood vessels
不是微血管 是動脈的血管
arteries like this
這樣子的動脈血管
can even help inside our rotorrat
甚至可以幫助在我們的轉子鼠裡面
to prove that it can grow new cardiac tissue
去證明說它可以長出新的心肌的組織
These new cardiac tissues
這些新的心肌的組織
It was born from the relationship report
是從幹系報說演生來的
I finished the first part
我完成了第一個部分
In the second part, I will go further to introduce this
第二個部分我要再進一步去介紹這個
How do we do tissue engineered myocardial regeneration
我們怎麼樣去做組織工程的心肌再生
This is actually my postdoc boss.
這其實是我博士後的老闆
One that Yu Qiuli and the others sorted out before
玉秋麗他們在之前所整理的一個
for heart cell therapy
要做心臟的細胞治療
What difficulties and problems will you encounter?
會遭遇到的哪些的困難 哪些的問題
You need to report treatment
你要做幹系報治療
Of course you have to have a relationship report first
當然你要先有幹系報
Where did this relationship report come from?
那這個幹系報從哪裡來
Is it to be derived from the relationship between embryos in the early stage?
是要從胚胎早期的幹系報所演生出來的呢
Still have to extract it from the body
還是要從身體裡面去把它萃取出來的
which one is better
到底哪一個比較好
this is a big problem
這是一個大的問題
The second question is
第二個問題是
Okay, I already have a relationship report today.
好 我今天已經有幹系報
become cardiomyocytes
會變成心肌細胞
Then how do I report this relationship?
那我怎麼樣把這個幹系報
sent to the heart
送到心臟
where i am going to be treated
我要去治療的位置
If you remember, I said at the beginning
大家如果還記得我一開始就講說
Although the heart will become so big in the end
心臟最後雖然會變得這麼大
to have a heart transplant
要做心臟移植
But when he first
可是他一開始的時候
It's just a local problem
只是一個局部的問題而已
Not the whole heart has to regenerate
並不是整個心臟都要去做再生
So when you're doing cell therapy
所以你要做細胞治療的時候
how do you get these cells
你怎麼樣把這些細胞
sent to where you want to regenerate
送到你要去再生的位置
Very important
很重要
Today if we want to rely on the head
今天如果我們要依頭
But all your medicine ran out
可是你的藥都跑到腳
or you have to lean on your feet
或者你要依腳
your medicine ran out
你的藥都跑到頭
of course it's useless
當然就沒有用
This is actually a very important
這其實是一個很重要的
a concept
一個concept
you may also
各位可能也會
sometimes want to say
有時候會想說
Why did the doctor tell me to take food today?
今天醫生為什麼叫我用吃的
Called me to call yesterday
昨天叫我用打的
even told me to suck
甚至叫我用吸的
stick to the skin
用貼皮膚的
Various
各種不同的
way to enter the body
要進入身體的途徑
In fact, he is not the same
其實他都不太一樣
the same reason
那一樣的道理
If we want stem cells
我們如果要把幹細胞
put it in the heart
放到心臟裡面去
you have to think
你就要想
How can I get stem cells
我怎麼樣可以讓幹細胞
can stay
可以留在
Can be injected where I am going for treatment
可以注射到我要去做治療的位置
do not forget
不要忘了
the heart keeps contracting
心臟一直在收縮
So you hit stem cells into your heart today
所以你今天把幹細胞打到心臟
no matter through point of view
不管 透過觀點
or hit the muscles directly
或是直接打到肌肉
24 hours later
24小時之後
Only 1% of the cells remain in the heart
只有1%的細胞還留在心臟
others ran away
其他都跑掉了
Even if the 1% of the cells left in the heart
即使這1%留在心臟的細胞
in 24 hours
再過24小時
Anyway, all 99 are dead
反正這99都死掉了
Only 1% are still alive
只有1%還活著
say it again
再說一次
Liver cells go to the heart
肝細胞打到心臟去
After a day only 1% is left
一天之後只有1%還留著
This 1% after another day
這1%再過一天之後
Only 1% are still alive
只有1%還活著
How much does 1% say that 1% is a student
1%稱1%是學弟多少
1/10,000
1萬分之一
another day
再一天
Gone
沒了
So after 10,000 cells hit the heart
所以1萬顆細胞打到心臟去之後
Save one in two days
兩天之後存一輛
Another day may not be gone
再一天可能也不見了
This is why we have many clinical trials
這是為什麼我們臨床試驗很多的
Cell Therapy in the Heart
細胞治療在心臟
In fact, there is no way to produce good results
其實沒有辦法產生好的結果
So how can more cells
所以怎麼樣可以讓更多的細胞
It's important to keep in the heart
會存留在心臟裡面很重要
and keep it alive
而且讓它活下來
not only survived
不僅活下來
it turns into cardiomyocytes
它要變成心肌細胞
with other cardiomyocytes
還要跟其他的心肌細胞
we become good friends
大家變好朋友
can shrink and jump together
可以一起收縮一起跳
not it
不是它
ok i stay
好我留下來
I change my mind
我變心
heart cells i will say
心機細胞我會說說
But I don't care about others
可是我不管別人的
i dance my own
我跳我自己的
that's bad
那糟糕了
what is that called
那叫做什麼
mental disorder
叫做心理不整
worse
更慘
really miserable
真的很慘
don't do it
不要做還好
you did
你做了
After taking stem cells, he was already a patient
打了乾細胞本來就病人
As a result, the patient caused him to go to the phone
結果把病人造成他要去電
going to CPR
要去CPR
something will go wrong
一定會出問題
So this is called
所以這個叫做
electricity
電
Integration of electrical conduction and details
電傳導跟細節的整合
why is it called
為什麼叫
Electro-mechanical integration
Electro-mechanical integration
Integration of electricity and details
電跟細節的整合
because our cells
因為我們的細胞
Between heart cells and cells
跟心機細胞跟細胞之間
by ionic conduction
是靠離子電性的傳導
electricity like this
電這樣
boo past
噓過去
Cells know one by one
細胞一顆一個才知道說
time to work
該工作了
It's time to shrink
該收縮了
just shrink together
就一起收縮
ions turn over
離子轉過去了
he has the swelling
他才有紓脹
So it needs to rely on the conduction of electricity
所以這是需要靠電的傳導
the heart must contract
那心臟要收縮
machine force
產生機界力
So this is the integration of the machine world
所以這個本來就是機界的整合
So this is called
所以這個叫
Integration of electrical and machine world
電性跟機界的整合
叫Electro-mechanical integration
叫Electro-mechanical integration
So the stem cells we injected
那因此我們打進去的乾細胞
It needs to be able to become a heart cell
它要能夠變成心機細胞
but also with other
還要跟其他的
The original cells of the heart integrate together and dance together with hands
心臟的原來的細胞一起整合一起手手一起跳
otherwise there will be big problems
不然就會出大問題
Then this cell therapy only in the heart
那這個只有在心臟的細胞治療
will face the problem
才會面對的問題
Cell therapy of organs from other tissues
別的組織的器官的細胞治療
will not cause this problem
都不會產生這種問題
Then if someone is nervous here, someone will tell me arque
那在這如果做神經有人就會跟我arque說
Hey, nerves also conduct electricity.
誒 神經也是靠電傳導啊
Then why didn't the nerves take up this problem?
那為什麼神經就沒有招臂到這個問題
then i'll joke
那我就會開玩笑說
If your nerve cell therapy
如果你的神經細胞治療
not doing well it goes wrong
沒有做得很好它出問題
At best you ask the patient to raise his right hand
頂多你叫病人舉右手
It kicks your left foot with you, it won't die
它跟你踢左腳嘛 不會死掉
Yes, but if something goes wrong with the cell therapy for the heart
對 可是心臟的細胞治療如果出問題
obviously something goes wrong
明顯就會出問題
would be a big problem
就會很大的問題
So this is still different
所以這個還是不太一樣
In the end, of course, we are doing clinical cell therapy
那最後當然我們在做臨床的細胞治療
is to consider its safety and stability
是要考慮它的安全性 穩定性
this is very important
這個都是很重要的
Let's first talk about how the cells
我們先來講怎麼樣把細胞
Get to where you are going for treatment
搭到你要去做治療的位置
Then we use a
那我們利用一個
Water glue called Eco-resistant rice fiber
叫做生態的耐米纖維的水膠
This water gel is from when we were at MIT
這個水膠是我以前我們在MIT的時候
Developed in partnership with MIT
跟MIT的股合合作發展出來的
it's basically a unit of protein
它基本上是一個蛋白質的單位
specially synthesized
所特殊合成的
special sequence of amino acid synthesis
胺基酸合成的特殊的一個序列的水澆
This water can be brought
這個水澆可以拿來
We inject directly into the site of myocardial ischemia and hypoxia
我們直接注射到心肌缺血缺氧的位置
we can put special drugs
我們可以把特殊的藥物
special cells
可以把特殊的細胞
Follow this water to directly hit the damaged heart muscle
都跟著這個水澆直接打到心肌受損的位置
This is the result of some of our previous research
這是我們一些之前的研究的結果
with some patents
跟一些專利
what you saw earlier
前面所看到這些
You may not know these
大家可能不太知道這些
what does this mean
後面這代表什麼
This is the name of each journal
這是每一個期刊的名字
These are all good journals like this
這些都還滿不錯的期刊這樣子
But those are small animals
不過那些都是小動物
we are doing animal experiments
我們在做動物實驗
We don't just bully mice
我們不只要欺負老鼠
In fact, we have to bully different animals
其實我們要欺負不同的動物
Because different animals have different characteristics
因為不同的動物有不同的特色
can represent different diseases
可以來代表不同的疾病
Usually we start with small animals
通常我們都會從小動物開始做
We will make the small animals bigger if they have results.
小動物有結果我們就會做大一點的
Make it bigger and finally be a human
再大一點 最後做到人
in our laboratory
在我們實驗室
In the field of our heart
在我們做心臟的領域裡面
Usually we use four animals
通常我們會用四種動物
Little mouse called Mouse
叫Mouse小老鼠
A rat named Red
一個叫Red大鼠
A rabbit named Rabbit
一個叫Rabbit兔子
and mini pigs
還有迷你豬
Meat pigs are one to two hundred kilograms
肉豬很大一兩百公斤
so we say mini pigs
所以我們說迷你豬
A mouse is about 25 grams
一隻小鼠大概是25克
Rat 250g
大鼠250克
Rabbit 2500g
兔子2500克
Mini Pig 25000g
迷你豬25000克
come to schoolboy or schoolgirl
來學弟或學妹
did you see anything
有沒有看到什麼
You're so smart, Shi Jingwei
對好聰明喔 石徑位
So if this represents the size of a mini pig
所以如果這個代表一隻迷你豬的大小
this is a rabbit
這個是一隻兔子
this is a rat
這個是一隻大鼠
what is this
這個是什麼
Friends sitting in the back maybe you can't see clearly
坐在後面的朋友們可能你看不清楚
What is this
這是什麼東西
So it's not the same from childhood to adulthood
所以從小的到大的其實不太一樣
because it's hard to say
因為很難說
i'm a little mouse
我在小老鼠做透
good result
很好結果
I'm going to do a human test tomorrow
我明天要去做人體試驗
probably won't work
大概行不通
not just like that
不只是這樣子
If we were in different animals
我們如果在不同的動物
we'll make it the same
我們就把它做同樣的
Surgical ligation Blood vessels tied up
手術的結紮 血管綁起來
human myocardial infarction
人的心肌梗塞
It also produces a different phenomenon
它也會產生不同的現象
For example, in terms of small animals
譬如說以小動物來講
where it produces a myocardial infarction
它產生心肌梗塞的位置
Most of them are on the outside of the left heart pose
大部分是在左心式的外側的位置
if it's a pig
那如果是豬
You do the same ligation
你同樣做這樣的結紮
where it produces a myocardial infarction
它產生心肌梗塞的位置
In fact, it is in two mental forms
事實上是在兩個心式中格
and the place ahead
還有前面的地方
This is exactly the same as a human
這個跟人一模一樣
So you probably can't do this
所以你大概沒辦法做這個
going to be a man
就要去做人
you have to do this
你要做這個
not just like that
不只是這樣子
If the same pattern of myocardial infarction
如果同樣做心肌梗塞的模式
In small animals only one
在小動物只要一個
It only takes one week in the small family
在小屬只要一個禮拜
it changes
它就變
Mind coins become so thin
心事幣就變這麼薄
It will take two weeks
大屬要兩個禮拜
Pigs are two months old
豬要兩個月一樣
like people
跟人一樣
So this is actually
所以這個其實是在
really tell you
實在跟各位講說
different animal patterns
不同的動物模式
In fact, there are different characteristics
其實有不同的特色
different needs
不同的需要
Then we use very smart
那我們用的是很聰明的
The National Treasure Pig is called the Blue Feather Miniature Pig
國寶豬叫做藍羽迷你豬
It has been pre-planted in Taiwan
它在台灣已經被預種
more than 100 years
超過100年的
From the time of the Japanese
從日本人的時代
has been preserved
就已經保留下來的
The Blue Feather Mini Pig
那藍羽迷你豬
Mini pigs, as the name suggests, of course happened in Orchid Island
迷你豬顧名思義當然是在蘭嶼所發生的
Produced in Orchid Island
在蘭嶼所產生的
But if you go to Lanyu today and you can't find Lanyu pigs
可是你今天要是到蘭嶼去找不到蘭嶼豬
please don't blame me
請不要怪我
Because Lanyu no longer exists
因為現在蘭嶼已經沒有
Lanyu mini pigs in stock
存種的蘭嶼迷你豬了
because it doesn't grow big
因為它長不大
So it can only reach forty or fifty kilograms
所以都只能到四五十公斤
so you feed it
所以你養它去
going to be a pig
要去當肉豬
It's useless to raise like this
這樣去養是沒有用的
it just doesn't grow up
它就是長不大
So now Lanyu is
所以現在的蘭嶼都是
The pigs in Lanyu are all mixed
蘭嶼的豬都是混的
all big ones
都是大隻的
you can't find this kind of pig
你找不到這種豬了
So luckily the Council of Agriculture kept it
所以還好有農委會把它保存下來
We use these Lanyu mini pigs
我們使用這些蘭嶼的迷你豬
From March 2009 to the end of last year
從2009年3月到去年年底
We are like this in Xinji Gengshe
我們在新濟梗社這樣子的
Take the mini pig for our animal model
拿迷你豬來做我們的動物模式
We made a total of 297 pigs
我們一共做了297頭豬
The meeting is like saying that I am not in Tainan now
開會像說我現在不在台南
I'm in Taiwan
我在台地
We use different control groups
我們利用不同的控制組
Either Xinji Terrier Society or treatment
或者是新濟梗社或者是做治療
its death
它的死亡
The whole surgical factor is still very dangerous
整個手術因素還是很危險
Its overall mortality rate is about 4.4%.
它整個的死亡率大概是4.4%
Probably the best result in the world
大概是全世界最好的結果
Then our first study is to simulate
那我們的第一個 study 就是在模擬
How to use the pig model to do clinical
怎麼樣用豬的模式來做臨床上
How do we do cell therapy
我們要怎麼樣去做細胞的治療
The first study we did was to grind the pig down
那第一個 study 我們做的就是把豬磨倒
Come on, whether it's a pig or a monkey I used to make
拜託 不管是豬還是我以前做的猴子
Or treat us all like human beings
或者是把我們都把它當做人一樣的對待
Has its own house suite
有它專屬的房子套房
It has its own operating room
有它專屬的手術室
It has its own anesthesiologist doing it
有它專屬的麻醉科醫師在做
They are treated exactly the same as people
都是跟人完全一模一樣的對待
Then after we grind down the pig
那我們把豬磨倒之後
we take its marrow
我們取它的骨髓
Take ten CC of bone marrow
抽十CC的骨髓
enough cells
就可以得到足夠的細胞
Why? Because we take this bone marrow out
為什麼?因為我們把這個骨髓拿出來
We extract its monocytosphere cells
我們萃取它的單合球細胞
Then mix with our rice fiber water glue
再混著我們的耐米纖維水膠
Then hit the damaged heart muscle
再打到這個心肌受損的位置
These cells do not escape
這些細胞不會跑掉
If you only play cells
你如果只有打細胞
Hit it in and it's gone
打進去 一下就不見了
So in America, abroad, even in Taiwan
所以在美國 在國外 甚至在台灣
If you only make cells for clinical trials
如果你只打細胞要做臨床試驗的話
How much bone marrow do you draw from the patient
你要跟病人抽多少骨髓
so you know what?
所以你知道嗎?
To 1200CC is easy to say
到1200CC說起來很容易
But patients turn on you like this
但是病人會跟你翻臉這樣子
because you scored
因為你打進
get a lot of cells
得到很多的細胞
Most of them don't see it
打進去大部分都不見得
just stay there a little bit
才一點點留在那裡
to see a little effect
才可以看到一點點效果
We only need to pump 10CC
我們只要抽10CC就好
Because our cells don't run away
因為我們的細胞不會跑掉
Wherever you type it is there
打進去在哪裡它就在那裡
So it will be better
所以它會比較好的結果
We found that the practice
我們發現這樣的做法
One month after the rent is completed
在租做完之後的一個月
We I just said two months
我們 我剛剛說兩個月
only one month here
這裡只有一個月
please don't blame me
請不要怪我
Because we're doing rental Starlet for the first time and say
因為我們第一次做租的Starlet說
We don't have much experience ourselves
我們自己也不太有經驗
so we don't know we have to wait two months
所以我們不曉得要等兩個月
we'll just do it for a month
我們就做一個月而已
but luckily
不過很幸運的
It will be good in a month
一個月結果就滿好的
We make Zhu Ye the Xingdao tube
我們把朱也做星島管
to see how his heart works
去看他心臟的功能
just found out
就發現說
If we only have to use the water glue of this rice
如果我們只有打這個耐米的水膠
after going in
進去之後
Although Zhu's contractile function is not better
朱的收縮功能雖然沒有比較好
But the flexibility of the chapters is better
但是書章的彈性是比較好
Because his pen won't get thinner
因為他心思筆不會變薄
If we only play cells
我們如果只有打細胞
His contraction function will help a little
他的收縮功能會有一點幫助
But it doesn't help the chapter function
但對書章功能沒什麼幫助
because he can protect
因為他可以保護
Protect the myocardium and reduce his necrosis a little
護心肌減少一點他的壞死
But things will still get thinner
可是心事比還是會變薄
When we combine this hydrogel with bone marrow cells
當我們把這個水膠跟骨髓細胞
when playing together
一起打的時候
I can make his heart at the same time
我就可以同時讓他的心臟
Both porosity and porosity function have become better
疏鬆跟疏鬆的功能都變得更好
why?
為什麼呢?
because if we take this cell
因為如果我們把這個細胞
Use the software of Red Silver Light to go
利用紅銀光的軟體去
to feed it
去餵食它
those cells will glow
那這些細胞就會發光
Then these cells follow our hydrogel
那這些細胞跟著我們的水膠
after hitting the heart
打到心臟去之後
a month later
一個月之後
we can still see him
我們還可以看到他
Many are still in the heart
很多都還留在心臟裡面
So because the cells don't run away
所以因為細胞不會跑掉
So it will work better
所以它才會比較好的效果
Then we learned
後來我們就學到了
one month is not enough
一個月是不夠的
so we just do it longer
所以我們就做更長的時間
do it for three months
做到三個月
It turned out that after three months
結果三個月就發現說
If only cell
如果只有打細胞
One month he helped the systolic function
一個月他對收縮功能有幫助
gone in two months
兩個月就沒了
if water glue
如果打水膠
His heart's systolic function isn't helping
他心臟的收縮功能沒有幫助
But loose function can last
但疏鬆功能可以持續
three months no problem
三個月沒問題
Do two Ken love each other?
兩個肯不愛在一起
Combining the two gives
結合兩個就可以得到
long time three months
長時間三個月
to three months later
到三個月之後
Both can have a greater effect on the function of the heart
都可以對心臟的功能有更大
Protect
保護
why
為什麼呢
Because our water degrades very slowly
因為我們這個水澆它的降解很慢
You know we often use some
各位知道我們常常用一些
Absorbable sutures to heal the wound
可吸收的縫線去做傷口的風和
you don't have to guess the line
你就不用猜線
It each a different absorbable thread
它每一種不同的可吸收的線
Its degradation rate is different
它的降解速率都不一樣
If it's faster, you want it to degrade as soon as possible
比較快的你就希望它趕快降解
It takes a long time and you hope it doesn't degrade too early
需要比較久你就希望它不要太早降解
Our materials will take 3 to 4 months
我們這個材料它要3到4個月
3 to 4 months after entering
打進去之後3到4個月
It will be completely degraded by the plant heart
它才會完全被株心來降解
So as it degrades
所以在它降解過程當中
it will attract
它就會吸引
It turns out that the cells in the own strain
原來自己株裡面的細胞
run to where we hit
跑到我們打的位置
generate more positive
產生更多的積極
more blood vessels
更多的血管
So mind coins don't get so thin
所以心事幣就不會變得那麼薄
This is what we use
這是我們利用
HPLC flutter analyzer to quantify the results
HPLC 支撲儀去定量出來的結果
the next question is
下一個問題是
what we did before
我們前面做的
To be honest, I really don't have much experience.
老實講也真的不太有經驗
Although they all publish good articles like this
雖然都發表還不錯的文章這樣子
But what we don't know much about
但是我們不太知道的是
What we did before was pigs tying up the big blood vessels
我們之前做的都是豬把大血管綁起來
Myocardial infarction is involved, get treatment quickly
心肌梗涉了 趕快做治療
But will it be like this clinically?
但臨床上會不會是這樣子
Is there a time when a patient with myocardial infarction runs ahead of you?
有沒有時候病人心肌梗涉就跑到你的前面
Just say hurry up and call me, it's impossible
就說趕快幫我打 不可能嘛
So what we want to know is to say
所以我們想要知道就是說
Such treatment if after myocardial infarction
這樣的治療如果在心肌梗涉之後
Do treatment right away or wait a day or wait four days
馬上做治療 或者等一天 或者等四天
even wait seven days to do it
甚至等七天才做
Will it also work
它是不是同樣會有效果
It's all very simple
這些都是講的都是很簡單
It's all one sentence, but it takes a long time to do
都是一句話 其實但是都要做很久
cost a lot of money
要花很多錢
This is Zhang Mingyao and one of us
這是張明耀也是我們的一個
Ph.D.
博士班畢業的博士
He's at a muscle growth company in the south now
他現在在南部一家生肌公司
treat it like a baby
把它當寶貝一樣
he did many things
他做了很多事情
he found out
他發現說
If our treatment after myocardial infarction in pigs
如果我們的治療在豬的心肌梗涉之後
do it right away or one day or four days
馬上做或者一天或者四天
It will make the pig's heart function better
都會讓豬的心臟功能變得比較好
but if you do it in seven days
但如果在七天才做
sorry it's too late no help
對不起 已經太晚了 沒有幫助
why is it like this
為什麼會這樣子呢
because of myocardial infarction
因為心肌梗涉
But after that he had a big damage to his heart
但是這之後他雖然對心臟有一個很大的傷害
But in the follow-up, his injury continued
但是後續他這個傷害是持續在進行
After waiting for a long time, his heart function is getting worse
等月久了他心臟功能越來越差
so you wait until seven days to do it
所以你等到七天才做
His heart function has become worse
他心臟功能已經變得比較差了
And this systemic vocal response
而且這個全身性的發音反應
will make your bone marrow cells worse and worse
會讓你的骨髓的細胞變得越來越差
The ability to grow blood vessels is also reduced
長血管的能力也變差
So even if you use it for healing effect
所以你即使把它拿來做治療效果
not so good
也不是那麼好
so the sooner the better
因此越快越好
Well, then my dream comes again
好了那接下來我的夢想又來了
If one day we can be in Taiwan
如果有一天我們可以在台灣
There is a treatment center like this one
有一個類似像這樣的治療中心
I always think that we in Taiwan should have
我一直覺得我們台灣應該又有
To develop more sophisticated
要發展比較尖端的
relatively new technology
比較新的科技
With our good medical system
搭配我們這麼好的醫療系統
Instead of introducing foreign countries every time
而不是每一次都是在引進國外的
imported from abroad
引進國外的
We should have something we develop ourselves
我們應該有我們自己發展的東西
Our treatments are
我們的治療在
If after myocardial infarction
如果是心肌梗塞之後
Do it in four days and you will have better results
四天內做你就會有比較好的結果
So if one day we really are
所以如果有一天我們真的在
Taiwan can CREATE such a
台灣可以CREATE這樣的一個
when the treatment center
治療的中心的時候
As long as the myocardial infarction is within four days
只要心肌梗塞在四天內
can fly to
可以飛到
Come to Taiwan to receive this treatment
到台灣來接受這個治療
we can give you a better prognosis
我們就可以讓你有比較好的預後
It's better to walk out alive
比較可以活著走出去這樣子
In those four days, I could fly many laps in the Ninth Classic
那四天在第九經可以飛很多圈了
I hope one day this dream can come true
希望有一天這個夢想可以實現
that another interesting stardis
那另外一個有趣的stardis
Do we have to use nanofiber hydrogel?
我們一定要用奈米纖維水膠嗎
can we use other
我們可不可以用別的
This is another Ph.D.
這是另外一個博士班畢業的
Now postdoctoral fellow Chen Jianxi Dr. Chen
現在博士後 陳建希 陳博士
He takes hyaluronic acid
他拿玻尿酸
this is playing every day
這每天都在打
There are two kinds of hyaluronic acid in our clinic
我們臨床上的玻尿酸有兩種
one is knuckle
一種是打關節
This is degradable
這個是可以降解的
so it won't be long
所以打進去不久
it will be degraded slowly
它就會慢慢被降解掉
One is to hit this
一種是打這個的
Do you know what you are doing?
各位知道在幹什麼嗎
This is a glue face
這個是膠臉的
so it can stay longer
所以它可以留比較久
We use knuckles
我們用的是打關節的
because we don't want it to stay for too long
因為我們不希望它停太久
So if we take hyaluronic acid
所以如果我們是拿玻尿酸
with bone marrow cells
跟骨髓的細胞來做
Do the same for the treatment of myocardial infarction in pigs
一樣做豬的心肌梗塞的治療
Treating it will also work
治療它也是會有效果的
Because hyaluronic acid is originally
因為玻尿酸本來就是
Can help long-term students
可以幫助長學管
OK
OK
again
再來
Do I have to use paleo cells?
一定要用古誰細胞嗎
some patients are afraid
有些病人會怕
Whoever hears that they want to vomit ancient times will have weak feet
聽到要吐用古誰 腳就軟
Although only Shi Xixi
雖然只有石西溪
We found out that we might be able to take peripheral blood
我們發現說我們可能可以拿周邊血
Or take several generations of blood
或者是拿幾代血
Everyone knows we are in Taiwan
大家知道我們在台灣
We now have 100,000 tubes of several generations of blood
我們現在有十萬管的幾代血
stored in our cell bank
存在我們的細胞庫裡面
We found that in the pig mode
我們發現說在豬的模式裡面
We take generations of human blood
我們拿人的幾代血
This is a collaboration with Dr. Huang Xiaoyuan, Princess Stone
這個是跟石公主黃孝遠博士合作的
Take the blood of several generations
拿人的幾代血
Mixed with Ornithium and hitting the pig's heart
混著駁鳥酸在打到豬的心臟
the cell will be repelled say
這個細胞會被排斥說
We want to give anti-rejection waist
我們要給抗排斥的腰
I'm like an organ
我就像器官一指一樣
We found that the practice
我們發現這樣的做法
May also help the function of the heart
也可以幫助心臟的功能
So it's not just nano water
所以不是只有奈米水澆
Ornithotic acid can also
駁鳥酸也可以
Paleo-cells
不是只有古誰細胞
We can also take generations of blood cells
我們也可以拿幾代血細胞
can achieve good results
都可以達到好的效果
as long as the two are combined
只要兩個是結合在一起的
If you only hit cells, it's useless
如果只有打細胞 沒有用
It's useless to just fetch water
只有打水澆也沒有用
must be combined
必須要兩個結合在一起
The issue of ischemia was just mentioned
缺血性的問題剛剛有提過
parotid encephalopathy stroke
腮道腦變中風
Cheeky Heart Myocardial Infarction
腮道腥臟心臟心肌梗塞
There will also be big problems with the cheeks and feet
腮道腳也會出大問題
This is actually such a patient
這其實這樣子的病人
More patients than myocardial infarction
比心肌梗塞更多什麼病人
diabetic patient
糖尿病的病人
His blood vessels will be diseased
他血管會病變
will block in the end
到最後會阻塞
especially the lower limbs
特別是下肢
So you may have heard
所以各位可能聽過
Many patients with diabetes
糖尿病很多病人
his wound won't heal
他傷口不會癒合
black toes
腳趾頭會黑掉
so in the end it will
所以最後就會
amputated toes one by one
一根一根的腳趾頭被截掉
In the end the whole foot will be cut off
最後整個腳都要被截止
I have several such patients myself.
我自己就有好幾個這樣的病人
This is actually a serious problem
這其實是一個很嚴重的問題
Because more and more people with diabetes
因為我們糖尿病人越來越多
no medicine
沒有藥醫
sorry
對不起
Because of this vascular patient
因為這個血管病人
It looks like it was eaten whole in the end.
到最後好像都整個被吃掉一樣
So we can't do bypass surgery
所以我們沒辦法去做繞道手術
We can't place the price
我們也沒辦法放置價
only take medicine
只能吃藥
Make your blood less likely to clot
讓你的血比較不會凝固
accidentally bleeding
不小心還會出血
These patients are actually very poor
這些病人其實是很可憐
In the end there is no other way
到最後都沒有別的辦法
just want it
就是要
in this way
這樣子
When it comes to sick patients the main thing is to leave in the end
談到病人病人最主要最後會離開
Myocardial infarction or stroke
原因還是心肌梗塞或中風
But as long as he lives long enough
可是只要他活得夠久
he will be like this
他就一定會被這樣子
So is there any way we can get through
所以我們有沒有辦法能夠透過
The way we treat
我們這樣的治療的方式
Similar treatment modalities for myocardial infarction
類似的心肌梗塞治療方式
can help these patients
可以來幫助這些病人
Let him not be like this one day
讓他不要有一天要被這樣子
This is actually a very important
這個其實是一個很重要的
This is actually the first clinical trial we're going to do
這實際上也是我們第一個要做的臨床試驗
We started talking with the Ministry of Health and Welfare three years ago
我們從三年前開始跟衛福部
Department of Health
當時是衛生署
FDA
食品藥管理署
Apply for a clinical trial
申請要做臨床試驗
Then start because when you applied
那就開始因為當時申請的時候
Although we have published a bunch of articles
雖然我們有發了一堆文章
not bad article
還不錯的文章
but they're still scared
但是他們還是很怕
because never done
因為沒做過
No one in the world has done it
全世界都沒有人做過
So I explained that we have a lot of homework to do
所以交代了我們很多作業要做
Let's just do the same thing obediently
我們就乖乖的一樣一樣這樣子做
It's been three years now
做到現在已經三年過去了
we haven't been fully approved to say
我們還沒有完全被核准說
can do this clinical trial
可以做這個臨床試驗
But this year should be the last time
不過今年應該是最後一次說
should do this year
今年應該會做的
Because it's really the last step
因為真的走到最後一步了
We want our hyaluronic acid and water cells
我們希望我們的玻尿酸跟股水細胞
Or the treatment of hyaluronic acid combined with blood dripping cells
或者是玻尿酸結合滴帶血的細胞的治療
can start to help our patients
可以開始來幫助我們的病人
Can keep it from being amputated one day like this
可以讓它不要有一天被截肢這樣子
this
這個
The idea is actually very simple, just like before
idea其實很簡單就跟前面一樣
Hyaluronic acid itself will help grow blood vessels
玻尿酸本身會幫助長血管
After the cells of this water enter
這個股水的細胞打進去之後
won't run away right away
也不會馬上跑掉
So combining these two treatments
所以結合這兩個治療
May be able to grow better blood vessels
可能可以長出更好的血管
to help patients with these peripheral vascular components
來幫助這些周邊血管組成的病人
We did this more than two years ago
這個我們在兩年多以前
Have already applied to the NRPD program
就已經申請到NRPD的計畫
I have been stopping there waiting for the Ministry of Health and Welfare to say OK
一直停在那裡等衛福部說OK
We will
我們會在
In National Taiwan University Hospital and City University Hospital
在台大醫院跟城大醫院
Start our first issue
開始我們第一期
Phase II clinical trial
跟第二期的臨床試驗
hope
希望
this
這個
Can do it this year
今年可以趕快進行
let us
讓我們可以
could help these patients earlier
可以早一點來幫助這些病人
because even today every day
因為即使今天每一天
There are 19,000 patients in Taiwan
在台灣都有19000個病人
at risk of amputation
面臨被截肢的危險
so we just have to do it earlier
所以我們只要早一點做
maybe save a few legs
可能就可以救幾條腿
One leg represents a family
一條腿代表是一個家庭
not a leg
不是一條腿
The last thing I want to introduce to you is
最後一個要跟各位介紹的是
Wear a study of stem cells
佩戴幹細胞的study
ok we go here now
好 我們現在走到這裡
We can now wear stem cells
我們現在可以把佩戴幹細胞
Or a type of cells called IPS cells
或者一種細胞叫做IPS cells
induced pluripotent stem cells
誘導性多潛的幹細胞
That is, the Japanese mountain raw rice
也就是日本的那個山中生米
called what he did get
叫做他所做的拿到的那種
This study of the Bill Award
比爾獎的這個study
So it is not a problem to become a New Territories cell
所以要變成新界細胞也不是問題
But now we want to deal with this matter
可是我們現在想要來對付這件事情
good
好
Take cells to the New Territories to help these patients
拿細胞打到新界去幫助這些病人
The results of more than ten years of clinical trials
已經有十幾年的臨床試驗的結果
Today there are more than 10,000 patients worldwide
到今天全世界有超過一萬個病人
have received cell therapy
有接受細胞的治療
Mostly own bone marrow cells
大部分是自己的骨髓細胞
or peripheral blood cells
或周邊血的細胞
to treat his heart disease
來治療他的心臟病
Of course mainly abroad
當然主要是在國外
America Most Europe
美國 歐洲最多
over the past ten years
這十幾年來
Those 10,000 patients are registered
那這一萬個病人是有登記有案的
the unregistered one
沒有登記的那個
We didn't know it was registered
我們不知道就登記有案的
More than 10,000 patients have received this
超過一萬個病人接受這種
autologous cell therapy
自體的細胞治療
After more than ten years of such clinical experimental research
經過十幾年的這樣的臨床實驗的研究
come to two conclusions
得到兩個結論
First cell therapy to treat heart disease is safe
第一個細胞治療來治療心臟病是安全的
You don't have to worry about its side effects
你不用擔心它有什麼副作用
The second conclusion is cell therapy to treat heart disease
第二個結論是細胞治療來治療心臟病
is invalid
是沒有效的
or only slightly
或者只有一點點效果
or only a short-term effect
或者只有短期的效果
The main reason is what I just said
主要原因就是我剛剛講的
Called in and disappeared
打進去都不見了
But there's still something to do
可是還是有一些還是要做
A lot of things just develop slowly
很多事情就是慢慢的去發展下去的
Then one of them is France
那這其中一個就是法國
Feliz Mahlerchet
Feliz Mahlerchet
a friend
一個朋友
The clinical trials they did ten years ago
他們在十年前做的臨床實驗
made nine patients
做了九個病人
Take his skeletal muscle cells
拿他的骨骼肌的細胞
stem cells from his skeletal muscle
把他骨骼肌的幹細胞
differentiate it into muscle cells
把它分化成為肌肉細胞
into his own heart
打到他自己的心臟裡面去
Because skeletal muscle cells are very good
因為骨骼肌細胞很好
Our heart muscle regenerates poorly
我們的心肌再生能力很差
i just said
我剛剛已經講過了
But our skeletal muscle regeneration ability is very good
可是我們骨骼肌的再生能力倒是非常好
If you work hard to perform today
今天假如賣命演出
Hit hard and I may die a lot of cells
用力打下去我可能會死掉很多的細胞
But I also stimulated a lot of skeletal muscle stem cells
但是我同時也刺激了很多的骨骼肌的幹細胞
to regenerate my skeletal muscles
去再生我的骨骼肌
So these muscles are very good at regenerative
所以這些肌肉的再生能力很好
And it has a great advantage that
而且它有一個很大的好處是
It is not afraid of hypoxia and ischemia
它不怕缺氧缺血
If we compare skeletal muscle cells and cardiac muscle cells today
我們今天假如把骨骼肌細胞跟心肌細胞
grow together in a hypoxic environment
一起在低氧的環境下培養
In less than a day, these cardiomyocytes are probably dead.
不到一天這些心肌細胞大概都掛了
Skeletal muscle cells are still alive
骨骼肌細胞還是繼續活著
Can live for more than a week no problem
可以活一個禮拜以上都沒問題
is autologous
是自體的
muscles everywhere
到處都是肌肉
so you'd want to say
所以你會想說
how nice
多好啊
There is no better source of cells than this
沒有比這個更好的細胞來源
Why are you doing stem cells with him?
幹嘛去搞陪他幹細胞
But from early clinical events it was found that
但是從早期的臨床事件就發現說
These nine patients took their own skeletal muscle myocytes
這九個病人拿了自己的骨骼肌肌細胞
after hitting the heart
打到心臟去之後
There are five bars to install the electric shock device
有五格壓去裝電擊器
because it creates dysphoria
因為它會產生心力不整
that's what i just said
就是我剛剛講的
The two cells cannot combine
兩種細胞沒辦法結合在一起
Shrink and jump together
收縮一起跳
Because its electrical conduction mechanism is different
因為它的電性傳導的機質是不一樣的
even if it's your own
即使是自己的
So the electrical conduction to the skeletal muscle
所以電性傳導到骨骼肌
When it reaches the myocardium, it hits the wall.
到心肌它就撞牆了
It won't pass, so there will be arrhythmia
不會過去 所以就會產生心率不整
So obviously this won't work
所以顯然這個是行不通的
Another relatively new study
另外一個比較新的study
This is Xinyatu's collaborator
這個是信亞圖的collaborator
It's my big brother named Chuck Murray
是我的老大哥叫Chuck Murray
He is wearing stem cells in the United States
他是在美國做佩戴幹細胞
Become the most famous group of mental cells
變成心機細胞最有名的group
They published an article over a year ago
他們在一年多以前發表一篇文章
It is to take people's wearing stem cells
就是拿人的佩戴幹細胞
differentiate it into cardiomyocytes
把它分化成為心機細胞
Then beat it into the monkey's heart
再把它打到猴子的心臟裡面去
they first discovered that
他們第一次發現說
can be inside the heart of the long class
可以在臨長類的心臟裡面
To grow human brain tissue
去長出人的心機組織
this is a big big breakthrough
這是一個很大很大的突破
But they also found that arrhythmia
可是他們同時也發現產生心率不整
Why is the heart rate irregular?
為什麼心率不整?
The same thing, human brain cells are the same as monkey brain cells
一樣嘛 人的心機細胞跟猴子的心機細胞
Of course they won't shrink and dance together.
當然更不會一起收縮一起跳了
so how to decide this question
所以怎麼樣去決定這個問題
is an important question to decide
是一個很重要的問題要去決定
OK, let me introduce our two technologies quickly.
好 那我介紹很快的介紹我們兩個技術
That is, we use the technology of electric imitation silk and magnetic field nano
也就是我們利用電仿絲跟磁場奈米的技術
That is to say, we go to spray electricity to imitate silk
也就是說我們去噴電仿絲
spray it and it will run around
噴出去它會亂跑
But we use magnetic fields to structure
可是我們利用磁場去架構
The position of controlling the running of electric imitation silk is adjusted one by one
控制電仿絲跑的位置是一根一根調一調的
is permuted
是排列組合的
like this
就像這樣子
Then the control group and the experiment have a control group
那以對照組、實驗都有對照組
The control group is to spray it out and let it run by itself
對照組就是去噴出去讓它自己跑
So it produces this kind of running around
所以它就會產生這種亂跑的
such a random
random的這樣的一個
The nanofiber
這個奈米的纖維
Then we make it a patch for the new machine
然後我們把它做成新機的補片
So one is permutation and combination and the other is not.
所以一種是有排列組合一種是沒有的
Then we found that when we put the new machine cells
那我們發現說當我們把新機細胞
In the two new tents with vascular endothelial cells
跟血管內皮細胞這兩個新帳裡面
most important cell
最重要的細胞
A patch like this that is aligned in this arrangement
仰在這種排列組合align的這樣子的patch
it will grow out one by one
它就會一條一條長出來
Just like the mobile organization of our new account
就像我們的新帳的機動組織一樣
If you put it on the back of the random row
如果把它仰在那種隨便亂排的
its own random run around
它自己的隨便亂跑
Then we use a relatively new one called an atomic force microscope
那我們利用一個比較新的叫原子力顯微鏡
very nanometer very thin
非常奈米非常細的
to detect its contraction
去偵測它的收縮力
you can find out that
就可以發現說
If you compare cardiomyocytes with endothelial cells
如果你把心肌細胞跟內皮細胞
well aligned in this
仰在這種排列得很好的
When the surface of the myocardial patch
心肌補片的表面的時候
it will shrink better
它就會收縮得比較好
Jump faster and more regularly
跳得比較快 比較規則
Then we put this myocardial patch into
然後我們把這個心肌補片補到
Most of the MI-colored outside go
大數的心肌梗色的外面去
You have to line up, you can't line up some guides
你要排好 不能排點導的
Can't line up vertically
不能排垂直
We need to compare that fiber with the fiber of our heart
要把那個纖維跟我們心臟的纖維要
The angle must be right and not crooked.
那個角度要對好 不能歪掉
Put it on after it's done
對好了之後 放上去
Two months later, I will go for an ultrasound of the heart
兩個月之後去做心臟的超音波
will find out that
就會發現說
This is better
這樣子比較好的
Such myocardial patch
這樣的心肌補片
It will greatly help the function of the heart
會對心臟的功能產生比較大的幫助
do cardiac catheterization
做心導管
We can also do cardiac catheterization in mice
老鼠我們也可以做心導管
The same is true for the systolic function of the heart
也是一樣心臟的收縮功能
It will be better with the sparse expansion function
跟疏漲功能都會比較好
It will even reduce the area of ​​myocardial necrosis
甚至於會減少它心肌壞死的面積
and two months later
而且兩個月之後
This is the cardiac patch we implanted
這是我們所植入的心肌補片
upper cardiomyocytes
上面的心肌細胞
it will follow
它會排的跟
The structure of the scheming of the normal heart is
跟正常的心臟的心機的結構是
direction is exactly the same
走向是完全一樣的
So when we take this heart out
所以當我們把這個心臟拿出來
Give it a software that covers ions
給它打一個蓋離子的軟體
and then look at the way it conducts electricity
然後去看它的電性傳導的方式
will find that such
就會發現說這種
Scheming cells in permutations
在排列組合的心機細胞
send it up
把它送到上面去了
Such a scheming patch
這樣子的心機補片
will allow our electrical conduction
就會讓我們的電性傳導
From this scheming patch
可以從這個心機補片上面
It can be transmitted to a normal heart
一直傳到正常的心臟裡面可以很
MOOS passed smoothly
MOOS的很平順的傳過去
If you put it in that messy long
如果你是放在那個亂長的
the fiber
這個纖維上面
it produces a heartbeat
它就會產生心率不斬
This is also an easy study
這個也是易動的study
the other one
那另外一個
embryonic stem cells
我們知道胚胎幹細胞
islet pluripotent stem cells
跟幼島性多潛能幹細胞
can become heart cells
都可以變成心機細胞
Can be used for many purposes
可以拿來做很多的用途
Can do cell therapy
可以做細胞治療
can do drug development
可以做藥物發展
Can be used to explore the mechanism of disease
可以來做疾病的機制的探討
But from embryonic stem cells
但是從胚胎幹細胞
or IPS stem cells
或者IPS幹細胞
cardiomyocytes
所產生的心肌細胞
It's also the cell of the embryonic heart
它還是胚胎時期的心臟的細胞
not like our normal mature cardiomyocytes
不是像我們正常的成熟的心肌細胞
So the two are still different
所以這兩個還是不一樣
Although in theory
雖然理論上
You know it's very difficult for us to get cardiomyocytes
各位知道我們要拿到心肌細胞是很困難的
It may be difficult for you to tell patients
你可能很難跟病人說
sorry i want to study you
對不起 我想要研究一下你
why do you have this disease
你為什麼會產生這個疾病
Cut a piece of your heart and let me do some research, okay?
你心臟切一塊來讓我做一下研究好不好
Let me cut a piece of your head out
你的腦袋讓我切一塊出來
Why don't you just cut it into pieces?
你就乾脹切一塊可不可以
patients probably won't accept
病人大概不會接受
But today if I tell you
可是今天我如果跟你說
we have a technology
我們有一個技術
I just want to draw two CCs of blood with you
我只要跟你抽血兩CC
I can grow your embryonic stem cells
我就可以養出你的胚胎幹細胞
I can differentiate it into cardiomyocytes
我可以把它分化成為心肌細胞
differentiate into nerve cells
分化成為神經細胞
differentiate into liver cells
分化成為肝臟細胞
to do research
來做研究
do you want to
這樣你願不願意
Probably most people will nod and touch to see
大概大部分人都會點頭摸看到的
cut a piece of heart you don't want
切一塊心臟你不願意
If you draw two CCs of blood, you will probably accept it.
抽兩CC的血大概你會接受
This is the purpose of our technology
我們的技術目的就是這樣子
I will continue to say this
這個我會再繼續說
mouse embryonic stem cells
我們現在老鼠的胚胎幹細胞
we made a
我們做了一個
gene transfer
基因轉職
The benefits of embryonic stem cells are
胚胎幹細胞的好處就是
it differentiates into the body
它會分化成為身體
more than two hundred cells
兩百多種細胞
Including what we usually dare not be cut
包括我們平常不敢被切的
cells of the brain
腦袋的細胞
Heart muscle cells Liver cells
心肌的細胞 肝臟的細胞
We can all use embryonic stem cells
我們都可以利用胚胎幹細胞
Or IPSL differentiates it
或者IPSL把它分化出來
Okay, so we did a genetic change.
好 那我們做了一個基因轉職
Let this embryonic stem cell angle
讓這個胚胎幹細胞角
it becomes cardiomyocytes
它變成心肌細胞
it will glow green
它就會發綠光
So we can use a machine
所以我們可以利用一個機器
cell separator
叫細胞分離機
purify these cells
把這些細胞純化出來
then we found these
那我們發現這些
green cardiomyocytes
發綠光的心肌細胞
it is immature
它是不成熟的
But if it compares with vascular endothelial cells
可是它如果跟血管內皮細胞
grow together grow together
一起生長一起培養
it'll start on day one
它就會開始在第一天
start after day three
第三天之後開始
Line up one by one
一條一條的排排站
like our base fresh tail
就像我們的基鮮尾一樣
And it has a better base fresh tail structure
而且有比較好的基鮮尾的構造
then you just ask
那你就問說
what endothelial cells do
內皮細胞做了什麼事
original endothelial cells
原來內皮細胞
it can be released
它可以釋放
it can help this
它可以幫助這個
produce some tiny tiny
產生一些很小的微小的
RNA
RNA
called microRNA
叫做microRNA
So when we put
所以當我們把
Find these four important
找出這四個重要的
The MICRO-RNA we want is called 125B199A21222
我們要有的MICRO-RNA叫125B199A21222
Treat these four MICRO-RNAs as drugs
把這四個MICRO-RNA當作藥物這樣去治療
to add to this immature scheming cell
去加到這個不成熟的心機細胞的時候
it becomes more mature
它就會變成比較成熟的
And these four MICRO-RNA
而且這四個MICRO-RNA
Their mechanism of action has a specific...
他們的作用機制都有一個專...
our MICRO-RNA this tiny nuclear soup nucleic acid
我們MICRO-RNA這種微小的核湯核酸
It usually has hundreds of mechanisms of action
它通常有幾百個作用的機制
There are 10,000 to 20,000 voices
機音有1、2萬個
But every MICRO-RNA
但是每一個MICRO-RNA
It has a different mechanism of action
它有不同的作用的機制
It's funny that the four of us
很有趣的是我們這四個
it actually has the same goal
它居然有同一個目標
the same mechanism of action
同一個作用的機制
This gene is called ERB4
這個基因叫做ERB4
This gene was found in early Tibet
這個基因是在新藏早期
A gene important in embryonic development
胚胎發育的時候很重要的一個基因
But once you mature and become an adult
可是一旦你成熟變成成體之後
The gene is gone
這個基因就不見了
it doesn't express
它就不表達了
We found that our MICRO-RNA
我們發現我們的MICRO-RNA
is acting on this gene
是作用在這個基因
So when we directly in this scheming cell
所以當我們直接在這個心機細胞
When this gene suppresses it
把這個基因把它壓下去的時候
It will grow more mature myocardial tissue
它就會長出比較成熟的心肌的組織
not just in mice
不只是在老鼠是這樣子
It's the same in humans
在人的也是這樣子
human embryonic stem cells
我們把人的胚胎幹細胞
become cardiomyocytes
變成心肌細胞
It also started as an embryonic entity
它一開始也是像胚胎實體的
But after the four of us
可是經過我們這個四個
After treatment with micro-RNA drugs
micro-RNA藥物的治療之後
It also grows more mature cardiomyocytes
它也會長出比較成熟的心肌細胞
its electrical conduction
它的電性的傳導
The amplitude of the image jump
形象跳動的幅度
like mature cardiomyocytes
也會跟成熟的心肌細胞一樣
So this is one of our models
所以這個是我們的一個model
This is our newest
這個是我們最新剛出爐
A newly graduated doctoral student named Keith
剛畢業的博士班學生叫凱斯
Because this study is in the Sale Report
因為這個study在Sale Report
is his cover story
是他的封面故事
So if you notice the news
所以各位如果注意到新聞
It seems to be noisy
好像吵得還滿兇的
It's so loud
吵得還滿大的這樣子
But everyone seems to be very interested in it
但是大家好像對它特別有興趣
so everyone asks
所以每個人都來問說
where is your student
你那個學生在哪裡
we are going to visit him
我們要去訪問他
Our model is through
我們的model就是經過
immature embryonic stem cells
把這些不成熟的胚胎幹細胞
derived cardiomyocytes
衍生的心肌細胞
cultured with endothelial cells
跟內皮細胞一起培養
It will stimulate these four chronic
就會刺激又發這四種慢性
It will always be ERBV4 this gene
它會一直ERBV4這個基因
Let immature scheming become mature scheming
讓不成熟的心機變成成熟的心機
and interestingly
而且很有趣的是
Such a heart cell
這樣子的心機細胞
We only need one treatment after giving this drug
我們只要治療一次給這個藥物之後
to 60 days later
到60天之後
This accumulation of tissue between each cell
每一個細胞之間的這個積結組織
This is to prevent mental disorder
這個是來預防心理不整的
it can grow very well
它都可以長得非常好
So these cells can be used for great purposes
所以這些細胞可以拿來做很大的用途
so as it may generate
所以因為它可能所產生
Such a large potential application
這麼大的一個potential的應用
With the support of NRPV
在NRPV的支持之下
Just now the vice president mentioned
剛剛副院長有提到的
We are different units from Taiwan for stem cells
我們跟台灣做幹細胞的不同的單位
some good friends some seniors
一些好朋友一些前輩
join together
大家一起結合起來
we have a goal
我們有一個目標
I just hope to help stem cells in Taiwan
就是希望能夠幫台灣的幹細胞
do something
做一些事情
what to do
做什麼呢
we set up a core facility
我們就成立一個核心的設施
Then come to help clinical doctors in Taiwan
然後來幫台灣的臨床的醫生
Want to do this Yushima sex more adult
想要去做這個佑島性的多成年
Stem Cell IPSL
幹細胞IPSL
to help them do
來幫助他們做
because it takes a lot of time
因為它要花很多的時間
a lot of energy
很多的精力
It's not easy to do and it even costs a lot of money
也不太容易做 甚至要花很多錢
We hope that such a coalition can be produced
我們希望可以產生這樣的一個聯盟
Help Taiwan do this
幫助台灣做這樣子的
iPS stem cells
iPS的乾細胞
The goal is to have it by the end of next year
目標是要在明年的年底的時候
We're going to make 100
我們要做出100個
Stem cells made from patients with 100 diseases
100個疾病的病人所做出來的乾細胞
and store it in
然後把它儲存在
The Food Industry Institute invites people from all over Taiwan to do research
食工所讓全台灣做研究的人
can apply for
都可以去申請使用
it will make a big difference
它會產生很大的作用
Because these iPS
因為這些iPS
Well-intentioned and fruitful stem cells
又好心有多成的乾細胞
like i just said
就像我剛剛說的
I don't need to take yours and cut your heart
我不需要拿你的 切你的心臟
no need to cut your head off
不需要切你的腦袋
No need to cut your liver
不需要切你的肝臟
I just need to draw two cc of blood
我只要抽兩cc的血
I can turn it into your own stem cells
我就可以把它變成你自己的乾細胞
and differentiate it into these cells
再把它分化成為這些的細胞
for disease research
來做疾病的研究
for drug screening
來做藥物的篩選
for personalized medicine
來做個人化的醫療
so one day
所以有一天
Now it's slowly starting to happen
現在已經開始慢慢要發生了
This technology will develop to
這個技術會發展到
if there is a patient
假如有一個病人
he has cancer
他得了癌症
he has to do chemo
他必須要做化療
But we know that many chemotherapy drugs
但是我們知道很多的化療藥物
he will be cardiotoxic
他會有心臟的毒性
Many clinical patients
臨床上很多的病人
After chemotherapy for his cancer
他癌症做了化療之後
Cancer shrinks or even disappears
癌症變小了 甚至消失了
But the patient passed away with heart failure.
可是病人卻因為心衰竭而過去了
this is a serious problem
這是一個很嚴重的問題
If we have these technologies
如果說我們有這些技術
Applications to Personalized Medicine
應用到個人化的醫療
patient today
今天病人
we know you have cancer
我們知道你得了癌症
One day you may have to do chemotherapy drugs
有一天你可能必須要做化療藥物
let me borrow it from you first
先跟你借一下
Take two CG blood first
先抽兩CG的血
give us two months
給我們兩個月
even shorter time
甚至更短的時間
i can make your
我就可以做出你的
IPS stem cells
IPS的乾細胞
we can make your cardiomyocytes
我們可以做出你的心肌細胞
your liver cells
你的肝臟細胞
your nerve cells
你的神經細胞
Then let's test it for you
然後我們先幫你測試看看
What drugs are available in hospitals now?
到底現在醫院可以用的這些藥物
Which of these medicines is best for you
裡面哪一個藥對你最好
The least toxic and the best
最沒有毒性效果最好
so we can talk to you
所以我們就可以跟你講說
I'm sorry, you can't take this medicine.
對不起 這個藥你不能用喔
But it's best for you with this medicine
但是用這個藥對你最好
If we say we are in Taiwan
如果說我們在台灣
Especially through Taiwan BioBank
尤其透過現在台灣BioBank
Taiwan Biobank
台灣生物資料庫
this one in Taiwan
台灣的這個
Now we're doing this
現在我們在做的這個
200,000 patients draw blood
20萬個病人抽血
Then do research every 5 years
然後每5年做研究
inside this database
這個資料庫裡面
We can choose the most
我們可以去選擇最具有
most representative genotype
基因型最具有代表性的人
then each of us
然後我們每一個人
make it all IPSL
都把它做出它的IPSL
save it all
都把它存起來
These 50 people can represent
這50個人就可以代表
More than 70% of the people in Taiwan
全台灣70%以上的人
His genotype will be very similar
他的基因型都會很類似
So one day if we were to use him as a representative
所以有一天如果我們要拿他來做代表
even take him
甚至要拿他來
Differentiate it into cells for cell therapy
把它分化成為細胞來做細胞治療
as long as people in Taiwan
只要是在台灣的人
you have a 70% chance
你有70%的機會
can be found inside these 50 stem cells
可以在這50個幹細胞裡面找到
with you can use
跟你可以用的
Can be used as a cell chair
可以來做細胞椅子的
like an organ chair
就像可以做器官椅子的一樣
This will have a big impact
這會產生很大的impact
even say that we can put this
甚至於說我們把這個可以
Although only 50
雖然只有50個
But it can represent 70% of
可是它可以代表70%的
Taiwanese genotyped cells
台灣人的基因型的細胞
turn it into cardiomyocytes
都把它變成心肌細胞
turn it into nerve cells
都把它變成神經細胞
turn it into liver cells
都把它變成肝臟細胞
I just said one day we'll have a
我就說有一天我們就會有一個
Taiwanese special heart chip
台灣人特殊的心臟晶片
Taiwanese special liver chips
台灣人特殊的肝臟晶片
Taiwanese special neural chip
台灣人特殊的神經晶片
We can do drug screening
我們可以來做藥物的篩選
We can come and check for disease
我們可以來做疾病的檢查
Personalized medicine, of course
當然可以做個人化醫療
That's what we're talking about
也就是我們現在在講的
future clinical trials
以後臨床試驗
No need to actually capture 100 patients
不需要真的把100個病人抓來
Give him this medicine and try to see if there is any response
都給他餵這個藥試試看有沒有反應
We just have to test it on this wafer
我們只要在這個晶片上面去做測試
It is possible to obtain the most preliminary results
就可能可以得到最初步的結果
So this is called what we are talking about now
所以這個叫做現在講的
clinical trials on a chip
在晶片上面做臨床試驗
or a clinical trial in a test tube
或者是在一個試管裡面做臨床試驗
就Cinco Trial on a chip
就Cinco Trial on a chip
or Cincotrile in a tube
or Cincotrile in a tube
that's what we're going to do
就是我們要做這個
this this this
這個這個
The reason for the project
project的理由
Then we took the traditional one, of course.
那我們採取了當然是傳統的
This way of life in Shandong
山東生命的這個方式
Then we use the technology of Sentai virus
那我們利用是Sentai virus這個技術
IPS cells can be achieved by drawing blood
抽血就可以做到IPS cells
And in Taiwan we have six hospitals, partner hospitals
而且在台灣我們有六家醫院 合作的醫院
North, middle, south and east
北 中 南 東都有
It is National Taiwan University Hospital Taipei Veterans General Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine
就是台大醫院 台北榮總 中醫大醫院
City University Hospital, Gao Medical University Hospital and Tzu Chi Hospital
城大醫院 高醫大醫院 還有慈濟醫院
These are the patients we collect
這些都是我們收集病人
There are also sources of clinician collaboration
還有臨床醫生合作的來源
Our Biomedical Institute at the Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine
我們在中醫院的生醫所
At National Taiwan University Hospital, Taipei Veterans General Hospital, National Health and Rescue Hospital
在台大醫院 台北榮總 國家衛生醫救院
and construction
還有施工所
can do this kind of service
都可以做這樣的服務
Generate these IPS cells
產生這些IPS cells
After it's done, it will be sent to the biomedical center of the hospital of traditional Chinese medicine.
做好了之後會送到中醫院的生醫所
Let's do an analysis with the construction company
跟施工所 我們去做分析
confirm this is good
確認這個是好的
is available and can be stored
是可以用的 可以儲存
It is open to everyone to apply for and use
可以公開給大家去申請使用的
Then it will be placed in the construction site for everyone to apply
然後最後會放在施工所給大家申請
This is our whole consoling guy
這是我們整個consoling的人
The main manpower and the main manpower of our biomedical institute
主要的人力和我們生醫所的主要的人力
such a study
這樣的一個study
two months ago
兩個月前
Originally made an appointment with Xingai Amalaka
本來約好幸愛阿馬拉卡
Sanzhong uncooked rice
就三中生米
This is Mr. Toyota
這個是那個豐田先生
He used to be from Taiwan, he can
他以前是台灣 他可以
Zhongcai who beat Wuting Pharmaceutical Factory
打武庭藥廠的中財
Later, after retiring, I returned to Japan for more than half
後來退休之後回到日本再大半
has he been in taiwan long
他在台灣很久嘛
Long-distance relationship with Taiwan
跟台灣感情遠生
one of his favorite things to do
他最喜歡做的一件事情
It's like helping Taiwan to develop relations with Japan
就是幫台灣跟日本拉關係這樣子
so through his relationship
所以透過他的關係
I had an appointment to go with
本來約好要去跟
Meeting of Kunia Malaka
訓愛亞馬拉卡的Meeting
How to talk about this sea swan
說怎麼要去談這個海鵝座
because he does it
因為他是做這個的
Grandpa who did this
做這個的老祖宗嘛
so i don't want to talk about the winner
所以我不要講得得主
promised
約好了
But the day before, I was suddenly called to Tokyo
可是前一天突然被叫到東京去
prime minister
首相
What does the Prime Minister of Japan want from him?
日本的首相要找他要怎麼樣
So then they had Deputy Director
所以後來他們就有副主任
come out with us and talk like this
去跟我們出來談這樣子
They also want to be with us
他們也很希望可以跟我們一起
Do it together with us
跟我們一起合作一起做
this is what he said
這他講的
I don't know if I'm talking
我也不曉得是正在講
He said that the genetics of the Japanese are very similar to those of the Taiwanese
他說日本人的基因性跟台灣人很像
i don't know his
我不曉得他的
where did he come from like this
他是從哪裡來的這樣
But this kind of cooperation is always good
不過這種合作總是好的
I always feel that
那我一直覺得說
Taiwan happens to be in the center of the Asia Pacific
台灣正好是在亞太的中心
Taiwan also has the best in the world
那台灣也有全世界最好的
at least one of the health care
至少是之一的那個醫療健保
such a system
這樣的一個系統
so we have very good
所以我們有非常好的
basic research person
基礎研究的人
have good clinicians
有很好的臨床醫師
So if we can build it into a
所以我們如果能夠把它建立成為一個
Asia-Pacific One Biomedicine
亞太的一個生物醫學
biotechnology industry
現在講的生技業
such a central word
這樣的一個中心的話
i think we have a good chance
我覺得我們是很有機會
This will also be helpful for us
這個對我們也會很有幫助
This is also my cooperation with the dean and vice dean
這個也是我配合院長、副院長
There are also seniors who are working in many courtyards
還有在做很多院裡面的前輩
Hope to be in the National Biotechnology Research Area
希望能夠在國家生技研究區裡面
We can be able to do Taiwan's more cutting-edge
我們可以能夠做台灣比較尖端的
advanced such a creature
先進的這樣的一個生物
A development of the biotechnology industry
生技業的一個發展開發
In the end, of course we all have to thank us
那最後當然我們都要感謝我們的
cooperation partner
合作的夥伴
At the Bank of China Hospital, at City University, National Taiwan University Hospital
在中銀院、在城大、台大醫院
Construction Office, Ma Street, National Health Bureau Institute
施工所、馬街、國家衛生局院
And our cooperation abroad
還有我們在國外的合作的
HARBORS、STANFORD、UC San Diego、UCSF
HARBORS、STANFOR、UC San Diego、UC SF
This is the former academician
這是前行院士
and this group in Karliski Sweden
還有卡爾利斯基瑞典的這個群組
and Xiatu
還有夏圖
In addition our funding is
另外我們的 funding 是
Except for government agencies
除了政府的單位以外
We have some US pharmaceutical companies in the biotech industry
我們有一些生技業的美國藥廠
Bawasli European Army, Asbalanika, Takoda
巴瓦斯利歐軍、阿斯巴拉尼卡、塔克達
And Taiwan's Malidi Army and Rebus Army
還有台灣的瑪利迪軍跟Rebus軍
Foreign pharmaceutical companies and Taiwanese design companies
國外的藥廠跟台灣設計公司的
Support and cooperation
Support跟合作
that's our team
那這是我們的團隊
Current team at the firm
目前在生意所的團隊
Finally I'll just take a minute
最後我再花一分鐘就好
This is my doctor's teacher
這是我博士班的老師
Dr. A.S. Eli Cruz
Dr. Eli Cruz
he passed away last year
他在去年過世了
he is one of mine
他是我的一個
A role model for my life
一生我學習的模範
i just mentioned
我剛好有提過
he is in the hub
他在哈伯
Completed by Harper School of Medicine
哈伯醫學院完成
After getting his medical degree
拿到他醫學位之後
research training
研究的訓練
thirty years in seattle
在西亞圖三十年
build the entire surgical
建立整個外科的
The system of this study looks like this
這個研究的系統這樣子
he's always been great to me
他對我一向很大
I've always said he's the best teacher in the world
我一直說他是全世界最好的老師
the best person
最好的人
Anyway, among the tens of thousands of people in Huada
反正在華大幾萬人裡面
If
如果說
If everyone says only one person is good
如果每個人都說只有一個人是好人
everyone else is bad
別人都是壞人
that good man is him
那一個好人就是他
that's the kind of person
就是這種人
so
所以
He has always encouraged me positively
他一直都很正面的鼓勵我
So I don't have this teacher's encouragement
所以我沒有這個老師的鼓勵
I can go on. I have a very important one this time.
我可以走下去 我這次一個很重要的
But now he passed away last year like this
不過他現在去年過世這樣子
that's sad too
那也很難過的是
Mr. Li Xudong, former deputy director of our firm
我們生意所的前副所長李旭東老師
He also passed away last week
他也在上個禮拜過世這樣
Then he was the person who influenced me the most when I returned to Taiwan
然後他是我回到台灣影響我最大的人
because this can't go on
因為這個講不下去
I can't go on, I can't go on
這講不下去 講不下去
anyway he has always given us a very positive kind of power like this
anyway 他一直給我們很正面的那種力量這樣
Because when I was growing up
因為我之前在成大的時候
peace in the business
在生意所和平嘛
Come here two days a week
每個禮拜來這邊兩天
So the incident is here for over six years
所以事件是在這邊已經六年多了
And the time he is not in the event room is actually him
然後不在事件室的時間其實都是他
Because he still comes every day after retirement
因為他退休之後還是每天來的事件是這樣子
The student, he discussed with the student
那學生 他就跟學生討論
Taking care of the students, teachers, mothers, and the owners all provide delicious food for the students
照顧學生 師母 業主人都好吃的東西給學生
That's why the students all looked for him instead of me.
所以學生後來都找他 不找我
Because you find me, you say this to me
因為找我就對我唸這樣子
So then I said, teacher, please be a bit more white.
所以後來我就說 老師你半白一點
I'm half black and you want to be half black
我半黑一點 你要人半黑一點
Otherwise, students won't be serious about this
不然這樣學生不會很認真這樣
He wrote very good calligraphy
他寫了非常好的書法
he passed away last week like this
他在上個禮拜過世這樣子
I think
我覺得
I'll stop here
我講到這裡就好了
that has a little time
那有一點時間
still some time
還有一些時間
We can all come and continue the discussion like this
我們大家可以來繼續來討論這樣子
Excuse me
不好意思
Lali Lala talked a lot
拉力拉拉講了一大堆
Hope it helps
希望能夠有幫助
Let's work hard together
大家一起來努力
Thanks
謝謝
Thank you for the wonderful speech after the social
謝謝社交後的精彩的演講
yes see these people
對 看到這些人
go one by one
一個一個去
It's also very sad
也是很感傷了
Xu Dong and I are also very popular
我跟徐東也是很受
i didn't know he passed away
我不知道他過世了
But why do you write the number 24 here?
不過你這裡為什麼寫24號
The 24th is today
24號是今天
today is the 23rd
今天是23號
Today is the world wrong
今天是全球寫錯了
it was last saturday
是上個禮拜六
last saturday
上個禮拜六
OK
OK
good
好
I think there should be many
我想這裡應該有很多
I want to ask our teacher thank you
想要問我們謝老師的
Come
來
Thank you teacher for your wonderful speech
謝謝老師精彩的演講
That
那
What I'm slightly curious about is that
我稍微好奇一點的地方就是說
Great efforts have been made in
裡面做了非常大的努力
To allow cells to associate with therapeutic substances
要讓細胞跟相關的治療物質
Where
在哪裡
Then I have heard that there seems to be some methods, such as
那我有聽說過好像有一些方法就是比方說
where to stick it like a thing
像貼一個東西一樣把它貼在哪
Didn't notice you didn't use this method
沒有注意到你沒有用這樣的方法
I even saw that at the back of your speech you said
甚至我看到你演講的後面的地方有說
Make a scheming patch that works
做一個可以工作的心機貼片
I don't know if I have thought about it
不知道有沒有想過
That is to say, between the scheming patch and the necrotic scheming
就是說心機貼片跟壞死的那個心機中間
Maybe put that several different
也許放那個好幾種不同的
You can take this material to regenerate it
你們可以掌握的這種材料去讓它再生
Is it possible to do the same
是不是也可以這樣做
Or why you don't do it thank you
或是說你們為了什麼原因不這樣做謝謝
Because you want the cells of your scheming patch to be the same as the original scheming
因為你希望你的心機貼片的細胞可以跟原來的心機
The cells of the heart can integrate together
心臟的細胞可以整合在一起
So it's best to just
所以最好就是直接
close together
靠在一起
If there is a thing between you
如果你中間還隔了一個東西的時候
it might not work
它可能就沒辦法
lock together jump together
一起鎖鎖一起跳
the answer is as simple as that
答案就這麼簡單
Thanks
謝謝
Or about one in every thousand people in advanced countries will die suddenly
或先進國家大概每一千個人就會有一個是猝死
You also mentioned the research in this area of ​​Xinji Kesi many times
您這也提到很多次的那個新濟可塞的這方面的研究
I don't know if the best
我不知道說如果最好的狀況
It's the teacher, you have solved all the problems of Xinji Kesi
就是老師您把所有新濟可塞的問題都解決了
Then the rate of one in a thousand sudden deaths
那這個一千分之一猝死的這個比例
How much do you think can be solved
您覺得大概可以解決到多少
ok thanks this is an important question
好 謝謝這個是一個很重要的問題
We have a plan with Dr. Chen Shi'an from Taipei Veterans General
我們跟台北榮總的陳時安醫師目前有一個計畫
Because Dr. Chen Shi'an works as a psychological minister all over the world.
因為陳時安醫師是在全世界做心理部長是一個
I think being the leader is very important for a group
我想是領導者是很重要的一個group
Then all we have to do is say
那我們要做的就是說
For those patients who already know he already has a psych minister
對這些已經知道他已經有心理部長的病人
but don't know why
但是不曉得什麼原因
Similarly, we can't take all these patients to cut their hearts and cut them into pieces for examination.
一樣我們總不能把這些病人都拿來切心臟切一塊來做檢查
So we hope to draw blood from these patients
所以我們希望拿這些病人抽血一樣是抽血
Turn it into IPS cells and turn it into psycho cells
把它變成IPS cells再把它變成心理細胞
come and see him
來看看他
What's wrong with these new cells
這些新細胞到底出了什麼問題
The advantage of this is that
這樣的好處就是說
if you want to cut a sick heart
如果你要切病的心臟
At most, the patient will ask you to cut a small piece for research.
頂多病人讓你切一小塊做研究
A small piece with few cells
一小塊沒有幾顆細胞
only do it once
只能做一次
at most once
頂多一次
I will never let you do it the second time
第二次絕對不會讓你再做
But if we put his two thin blood
可是我們如果把他兩細細的血
Turn into IPS into new cells
變成IPS變成新細細胞
In theory we can get infinite
理論上我們可以得到無止境
New Cells with Unlimited Craftsmanship
無限工藝的新細細胞
can do a lot of research
可以來做很多很多的研究
with drug screening
跟藥物的篩選
This is also another
這同時也是另外一個
The Approach to Personalized Medicine
個人化醫療的方式
In other words, why the patient has been
也就是說這病人為什麼一直都
Anticardiac drugs have been doing poorly
抗心力不整的藥一直都做得不好
Sometimes it's even hard to control
甚至有時候控制都不好
what is the reason
到底原因是什麼
You can't always take his heart
你總不能把他心臟一直拿來
make slices for inspection
做切片做檢查
Even do the electrophysiology of the heart like this
甚至做那個心臟的電生理的這樣
Those are actually pretty dangerous
那些其實都蠻危險的
But we can put his
可是我們可以把他的
Blood-drawn IPS turns into new cells
抽血的IPS變成新細細胞
We can do drug screening
我們可以來做藥物的篩選
Mechanism of making drugs
做藥物的機制
Finally you can talk to him
最後你可以跟他講說
It turned out to be like this
原來是這樣子
This drug is actually the best choice for you
這個藥其實對你是最好的選擇
instead of asking the patient to
而不用讓病人去像
what are we
我們就什麼
be a white mouse
做白老鼠
In fact, many patients sometimes act as guinea pigs
其實很多有些時候病人在做白老鼠
The doctor is also working as a guinea pig
醫生也在做白老鼠
But the doctor loves the patient more and is the weaker side
可是醫生是比較愛病人是比較弱勢的一方
So if we use these techniques
所以如果我們透過這些技術
Let the patient know earlier
可以早一點讓病人知道說
In fact, what kind of drug choice is best for you
其實怎麼樣的藥物的選擇對你是最好的
This will be of great help to patients
這個會對病人產生很大的幫助
Emergy comes
Emergy來
ask the teacher
請問老師
The experiment you just talked about
你剛剛講的那個實驗
I need people and money
多需要人跟錢
but spend so much time
但又花那麼多時間
Is it faster if you give more money and more people
如果給你更多錢更多人是不是速度就很快
Turned ten years into one month
原來要十年變成一個月
will have such an effect
會有這樣的一個效果
If you have a big team
你如果帶著團隊很大
and many
而且很多
Is this progress so fast?
那這樣這個進度是不是很快
And you have made a lot of achievements
而且你這個成果共成了很大
I guess the question is a bit complicated
我想這個問題有點複雜
we can't say
我們也不可能說
Everyone don't do it, I just do it
大家都不要做我就我來做就好
Because there are quite a lot of complicated factors
因為這個有蠻多複雜的因素
but i am
不過我倒是
I don't know what the vice-president or the secretary-general think
我倒是想不曉得副院長或是秘書長怎麼看
because i have a friend
因為我有一個朋友
He is the leader of the Singapore relationship package like this
他是新加坡幹系包的leader這樣子
He is actually involved in many government policies
他實際上也參與很多政府的政策的
Policy formulation and budget allocation
政策的制定跟預算的分配
I envy him
我很羨慕他
Because every year he meets me, he tells me
因為他每一年遇到我都會跟我講說
How much more has our tech budget grown
我們科技預算又成長了多少
That's the latest I was last time
那最新我上一次就是那個
The meeting organized by NOVATIS at the Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine
NOVATIS在中醫院辦的那個會
He'll tell me about his tech budget
他會跟我說他的科技預算
I calculated that we were probably
我算了一下是我們大概是
Are we about 100 billion a year?
我們大概一年一千億嘛
almost
差不多
their annual tech budget
他們每一年的科技預算
Now it has grown to about 300 billion Taiwan dollars a year
現在已經成長到一年大概三千億台幣
ever less than us
從以前比我們還少
The population of Singapore is only slightly more than a quarter of ours
那新加坡人口只有我們四分之一多一點
So they're just over a quarter of our population
所以他們只有我們四分之一多一點的人口
His tech budget is three times ours a year
他的科技預算一年是我們的三倍
So it turns into saying
所以一來一回變成說
What is the average technology budget for each person?
平均每一個人的科技預算是多少
12 times
12倍
i remember i want to go abroad
我記得我要出國
1990 when going out
1990要出去的時候
I was already an old student
我那時候已經是老學生
What scared me that year was
那一年對我蠻嚇的就是
In 1999, Singapore decided to invest in the biotechnology industry
新加坡那一年1999年開始決定要投資生技業
So they started to spend 30 billion Taiwan dollars a year, and then they spent it like this
所以他們就每年開始300億台幣這樣就砸下去這樣
Later, it has been growing until now it is 300 billion
後面一直成長到現在是3000億
So I have to be honest and say that our research on dry bags is actually a lot behind Singapore.
所以我必須老實講我們的幹西包其實研究是落後新加坡不少
They can occupy a group overnight in the world and we can't
他們在世界上已經可以佔一組佔一夕之地我們還不行
so i think we might have to try harder
所以我覺得我們可能要再努力
Of course, if the government is in financial difficulties, everyone knows that under the circumstances of financial difficulties
當然如果政府財政困難大家都知道財政困難的情況之下
We may not be able to do everything, we have to pick some priorities to do
我們可能不能什麼都做我們就要挑一些重點去做
Maybe it's just like what the director of the upgrader district said, what we have to do
可能就像升級人區院長院總所講的我們要做的
Can't do everything but we have to do it best
不能什麼都做但是我們要做就要把它做得最好
Recently, with the representatives of the Netherlands in Taiwan, they are hoping to establish cooperation
最近有跟荷蘭駐台代表他們就在希望建立合作
Even encouraged us to go to the Netherlands to cooperate with us like this
甚至鼓勵我們去荷蘭跟我們合作這樣子
They say that even the technology of the world like the Netherlands
他們說即使是荷蘭這種世界的科技
Here in the powerhouse of biotechnology
這邊在生物科技的強國
They also only choose a few fields to work hard to do this
他們也只選少數的領域去努力去做這樣
will be competitive
才會有競爭力
I don't know if this will help us
我不曉得這樣是不是會對我們有幫助
If we say that this is a
如果說我們覺得這個是一個
We are worth investing in, worth doing
我們值得去投資 值得去做
In fact, there are some fields in Taiwan that are quite competitive.
其實台灣真的有一些領域是蠻有競爭力的
is quite competitive
是蠻有競爭力的
It will help if we do this
我們如果從這方面去做會有幫助
It’s like we established the console of the IPA club
就好像我們成立那個IPA社的console
In fact, it was proposed more than three years ago.
其實三年多以前就提出來的
but many people disagree
但很多人不同意
Reasons for disagreement will feel like saying
不同意的理由就會覺得說
Before doing stem cells in Taiwan, there were really few
台灣做干細胞前真的很少
It will be troublesome to talk about this
這個再講下去就麻煩了
If we use some of the resources to do this
如果說我們把其中一部分資源拿來做這個
then the others will decrease
那其他就會減少
but then again
不過話說回來
If we feel that this is the right thing to do
我們如果覺得這件事情是應該做的
we will do it
我們就去做
It's not about taking Nobio. It's already taken.
並不是為了要拿Nobio講已經拿走了
It is not for the cooperation of Nature Science
並不是為了要發Nature Science的配合
neither
都不是
It's actually for our own national health
實際上是為了我們自己的國民健康
For our research projects
為了我們的科研的計畫
For our basic strength
為了我們的基礎實力
So even if you don't want to take Nature Science
所以即使你不是要拿Nature Science的
I don't want to talk about it even if you don't want to post NATURE Science
那我不要講 即使你不是要發NATURE Science
You still have to do it and try to do it well
你還是要做 而且要努力把它做好
So we actually have the same scale
所以我們其實同樣的scale
The money we use is less than one tenth of that of foreign countries
我們用的錢只有國外的十分之一還不到
But I think it's time to do it
但是我覺得該做還是去做
So last year was our first project of the whole year
所以去年是我們一整年第一個計畫
Our laboratory has posted 3 million such
我們實驗室貼了300萬這樣
Mourn this to the vice president
跟副院長哀一下這樣子
I hope this year will not be like this, we will lose another 3 million like this
今年希望不要這樣 我們再虧300萬這樣
do it when it's time to do it
該做的時候還是要做
i always feel like saying
我一直覺得說
Everyone sitting here thank you so much
大家坐在這裡 很感謝這樣子
every dime
每一毛錢
it's all taxpayer money
這些都是納稅員的錢
including my own tax money
包括我自己納稅的錢
we can't run away for a dime
我們一毛錢都跑不掉
So it's really the responsibility to do it well
所以真的是有責任要把它做好
Can't be wasted
不能浪費
If I'm a student again, listen up
我如果再做學生 大家聽好
I've said it many times
我已經講很多次了
Our scientific research money is the taxpayer's money
我們科研的錢都是納稅員的錢
we can also waste
我們也能夠浪費
I want to ask that teacher
那個老師我想請教一下
You said two CCs of blood were drawn for the IPS
你說的抽兩CC血做那個IPS
Is it specific to your patients or in general
是針對你的病人還是說一般
People with average IQ can
一般智商人員都可以
It will be all right
都可以
are all
都是
how to express
那要怎麼樣表達
if i say yes
假設說我願意的話
then go
那要去
Even if you are not a patient
就是說不是病人也可以
Can IQ people do it too?
智商人員也可以嗎
I have to apologize to you for this
這個必須要跟你們抱歉
because it takes a long time
因為要花很久時間
spend a lot of money
花很多錢
if you are abroad
你如果在國外
you say
你說
i wish to know
我希望知道
I'm going to make my own IPSELS
我要做出我自己的 IPSELS
you need to spend at least thirty thousand dollars
你至少要花三萬塊美金
to be able to make your appearance
才能夠做出你的這個外觀
That is to say, I am willing to shed two nights of blood
就是說我願意出兩夕夕的血
I have to pay
我要付錢就對了
That is to say, if you want to make
就是說你如果要有做出
Your own cells that you can use in the future
你自己的細胞將來你可以用的
right
對
It's like this in foreign countries
在國外是要這樣子
what we do now
那在我們現在做的
We really have to be selective
我們就真的是必須要精挑細選
with object
有對象的
have a specific object
有特定的對象
yes
是
So if say
那所以如果說
you already know
你已經有知道
when your own genotype
你自己的基因型的時候
then we can discuss
那我們可以來討論
Thanks
謝謝
then you might be
那你可能會是
one of our rare
我們稀有裡面的一個
then we'll do it for you for free
那我們會免費幫你做
But you have to Promise
但是你必須要Promise
same idea
一樣的想法
that is
就是說
We donate with all of these
我們跟這些所有捐贈
including patients
包括病人
Including the doctor, we help him do it for free
包括醫生我們幫他免費做
it's government money
就是政府的錢
He wants to promise one thing
他都要promise一件事情
after making it
就是做出來之後
You need to be able to expose technology
你要能夠公開技術
for everyone to use
讓大家都可以去使用
Of course this patient donor profile
當然這個病人捐贈者的資料
we can't make it public
我們都不能公開
This IRB has that
這個IRB有那個
That must be protected by the Personal Data Law
那個必須要各資法要保護的
but you must agree to say
可是你一定要同意說
we do a good job for you
我們幫你做很好
And guarantee the best quality
而且保證是最好的quality
but you have to donate
但是你就要捐出來
available for everyone to use
可以提供給大家都能去使用
that makes sense
這樣才有意義
i mean
我的意思是說
is your object enough
你的對象已經足夠了嗎
we are still growing
我們還在增加當中
yes
是
We will have a more familiar problem
我們會有一個比較熟悉的問題
I've been doing this report for a while now.
這個幹系報告也做了一陣子了
Because now everyone cares about the biotech industry
因為現在大家都對生技產業很關心
Newspapers for the past two days
這兩天報紙
you can also see
你也可以看到
Our euro has always been long
我們歐元長也是一直
on board
在上來板面
this stem cell
這個幹細胞
What are the uses that are actually in use now?
真正現在有在用的用途是哪一些
Because you can also see that there are many companies
因為你也可以看到有很多的公司
As you said just now, the two details
像你剛才講這個兩細細的
There are also people who use chicken blood to save it again, etc.
也有人用雞帶血要再存起來等等
A lot of business activities are going on
蠻多商業的行為在進行之中
these things
這些東西
Is it all useful or is it
都有用嗎還是是
I'm not saying which stock I'm going to invest in
我不是說我要去投資哪個股票
But I really don't know
不過我真的是不曉得
these stem cells
這些幹細胞
current
目前的
Let me give you an example of what can be used in practice
實用上可以用在什麼東西我舉個例子
A few years ago because my teeth had to be treated
幾年前因為我牙齒要治牙
this bone is not good
這個骨頭不太好
they just
他們就
I just installed this bone powder, wait a minute, I heard that there are also stem cells in it
就裝了這個骨粉啊等等裡面聽說也有幹細胞在裡面
Then he promotes this
然後那他去促進這個
skeletal
骨骼的
the real body of my skeleton
我的骨骼的真身嘛
so that is
所以那個是
looks feasible
看起來是可行的
and already confident
而且已經在自信自信
So stem cells are now in
所以幹細胞現在在
What are the things that are generally used
一般有在用的有哪一些東西
Chairman, this is a big problem
會長這個問題很大
different stem cells
不同的幹細胞
Different stem cells have different uses
不同的幹細胞它有不同的使用
So far
目前為止
was in Japan
在日本被
There are three licensed products that are ready for commercialization
被許可的已經可以商業化的產品共有三個
The first one is whether you want to guess
第一個是各位要不要猜
what was the first stem cell product
第一個幹細胞產品是什麼
or products of regenerative medicine
或者是再生醫學的產品
Products for regenerative medicine including stem cell tissue engineering
包括幹細胞組織工程再生醫學的產品
The first product is
第一個產品是
Probably the skin, the skin is the easiest
大概是皮膚啊皮膚最容易嘛
So when we get mad, there are people in Japan who help
所以我們氣爆的時候日本有人幫忙
So their first product was
所以他們第一個產品就是
In the case of a burn patient
如果是燒傷的病人
he takes a small piece of skin
他取一小塊皮膚
Can give you the whole tablet within a week
可以在一個禮拜之內給你整片的
my skin looks like this
自己的皮膚這樣子
The second product is cartilage
第二個產品是軟骨
So using arthroscopic very small wounds
所以利用關節鏡很小的傷口
Take a small piece of cartilage and raise it a lot
取一小塊軟骨把它養很多
It's time to fix it
到時候可以來做修補
a month's time
一個月的時間
to repair your own cells.
就可以來做自己的細胞的修補
third heart
第三個心臟
The heart is the same is to take that
心臟是一樣是拿那個
top stem cells
尖子乾細胞
Muses Kamas stem cells
Muzen Kamas stem cells
it's the same as laying it on
它是一樣把它鋪在
A membrane called Ph sensitive
一個叫Ph sensitive的一個membrane
This is their Japanese unique technology
這是他們日本的獨特的技術
That is to say, the cells
也就是說把細胞
after planting on that membrane
種在那個薄膜上面之後
temperature change
溫度一改變
The film will roll up
這個薄膜就會捲起來
You don't need to knock it down
就可以細胞就不用把它打下來
it will survive better
它會存活得比較好
So this film can be attached to
所以這個薄膜就可以貼到
damaged surface of the myocardium
心肌受損的表面去做
It's the Sawar from Osaka University
就是大阪大學的那個Sawar
what they are doing
他們在做的
it was them a month ago
就是他們一個月前
Just been approved
剛被approved的
Japan Postsei approved
日本後生生approved
The third product looks like this
第三個產品這樣子
right
對
Didn't you use it when you pressed it?
你壓成那個不是都在用嗎
Um
嗯
do you really have stem cells or fake
你真的有乾細胞還是假的嗎
actually stem cells
其實乾細胞
a lot
很多啦
a lot of
很多
stick to stem cells a lot
堅持幹細胞很多
what you just said
那先您剛剛講的那個
Insistence on stem cells does exist
堅持幹細胞的確是有
And because sticking to stem cells
而且因為堅持幹細胞
Its purpose is to grow bones
它的目的就是要長骨頭嘛
long cartilage
長軟骨
So it's actually make sense
所以其實是 make sense
This is done in many places abroad
這個在國外已經滿多地方在做
just say a lot of stuff like this
只是說很多這樣子的東西
it
它
to Japan
以日本
Japan because of cell therapy
日本因為細胞治療
Go to the forefront and the fastest
走得最前端最快
In Japan
以日本來講
it's up to now really its epigenetic province
它到現在真正它後生省
Heke's company
合可的公司
Cellular products that can be made
可以去做的細胞的產品
just these three
就這三個
Everything else is done in the hospital
其他都是醫院裡面自己做
it's easy in japan
在日本很容易
we just talked
我們剛剛講說
Our cell therapy application for three years
我們的細胞治療申請了三年
still can't do it
到現在還不能做
In Japan as long as it is
在日本只要是它
Hospital IRB Consent
醫院的 IRB 同意
it can directly do
它就可以直接做了
No need to go through your epigenetic province
不需要經過你後生省的
this cartilage to
這個軟骨到
this joint this
這個關節的這個
Nearly the whole doctor is not there
將近全醫師不是也在
Do something like this?
做這樣子的事情嗎
That
那
Seems to be doing quite well
好像還做得滿不錯的
doing clinical trials
在做臨床試驗
right
對
still doing clinical trials
還在做臨床試驗
OK
OK
I don't know if there are any other problems
不知道還有沒有什麼其他的問題
no matter the heart
不管是心臟也好
or stem cells
或者幹細胞也好
very important now
現在很重要
I'm sorry, I'll just ask one more question
不好意思那我就再多請教一個問題
The teacher just mentioned stem cells and also mentioned that different countries have different degrees of loosening research
老師剛剛提到幹細胞也提到各個國家對於研究的鬆綁的程度不一樣
Now in Taiwan, I seem to have heard that if you are not very familiar with it, you can’t use Petai stem cells.
那台灣現在我好像聽說不是很熟就是佩泰幹細胞是不可以拿來用的
Then we need to untie this side so that researchers can dispute the use of
那我們需要把這邊鬆綁掉就是讓研究者可以爭議的使用包含佩泰在內的
Stem cells, do you think this is appropriate or something?
幹細胞你覺得這樣算妥當或是什麼
Petai stem cells cannot be used in advanced countries
佩泰幹細胞在先進國家裡面都還不能用在
human
人的
Except for very few clinical careers
除非很少量的臨床事業
All
都
No country has approved
沒有任何一個國家有核許
Petai Stem Cells Turned into a Product
佩泰幹細胞變成一個產品
for cell therapy
來做細胞治療沒有
Currently there is no
目前全世界都沒有
Because Petai Stem Cells
因為佩泰幹細胞
to not quite
到不完全是
Ethical considerations
倫理的考量啦
Because Petai Stem Cells
因為佩泰幹細胞
he has great potential
他有很大的potential
As I just said, he can become more than 200 kinds of physiological cells
剛剛說的他可以變成生理兩百多種的細胞
very capable
能力非常強
but you want only one of them
可是你要的只是其中一種
You injected embryonic stem cells into the heart today
你今天把胚胎幹細胞打到心臟裡面去
Although it may grow cardiomyocytes
它雖然有可能會長心肌細胞
but it will grow other
但它也會長別的
in trouble
麻煩了
So we know very little about embryonic stem cells
所以胚胎幹細胞我們的了解其實還很少
So it's better to say
所以比較好的就是說
We call embryonic stem cells or IPSEL
我們把胚胎幹細胞或者IPSEL
turn it into various cells
把它變成各種不同的細胞
for drug screening, toxicology testing
來做藥物篩選 毒物測試
Discussion of genes, even personalized medicine
基因的探討 甚至做個人化的醫療
this is no problem
這個沒有問題
But if you want to turn these into a product
但是你如果要把這些變成是一個產品
it's more difficult
這是比較困難的
But there are many companies
不過的確有很多的公司
What you are doing now is just like what the vice president said just now
現在做的就像剛剛副院長有講的
That is, they store cells
就是說他們把細胞儲存
After storage, it can be made into various treatments in the future
儲存之後將來可以做成各種治療
For example, our
譬如說我們的
this should be able to speak
這應該可以講了
All papers have been published
paper都已經published的
sorry i go back
對不起 我回去一下
For example, that Selgen
譬如說那個Selgen
This is one of the largest pharmaceutical companies in the United States
這是美國前幾大的藥廠之一
Their strategy is the same as some companies
他們的策略跟一些公司一樣
that is to say they are
就是說他們在
Fascinity in GMP
在GMP的Fascinity
under the laboratory that meets the specifications of that drug
就符合那個藥品的規格的實驗室之下
just make it tube by tube
就做成一管一管的
various stem cells
各種不同的幹細胞
Then take this tube of stem cells as
那把這一管一管的幹細胞就當作
Think of it like stem cells are also drugs
你把它想像成幹細胞也是藥物
So when it uses this stem cell as a drug
所以當它拿這個幹細胞當作藥物
Do clinical trials of clinical treatments for different diseases
去做不同的疾病的臨床治療的臨床試驗
if it works
如果它成功了
In the future it will be approved by the US ADL
將來它被美國ADL approved之後
it can sell the drug
它就可以去賣這個藥
for example
譬如說
Of course, these are mainly diseases that cannot be treated at present.
當然這個都是只有現有沒辦法去做治療的疾病為主
rare disease
罕見的疾病啊
mainly
為主
then if it works
那如果它可以成功的話
Then it can sell you a tube of cells in the future
那將來它就可以把一管一個的細胞賣給你
as medicine
當作是藥
So this pattern is more
所以這樣的模式是比較多
Most of them are like this now
目前大部分都是這樣子
just say
只是說
approved but still very limited
被 approved 還是很有限
Are there any other questions?
還有沒有其他的問題
Our heart beats several times in a lifetime
我們心臟一輩子跳幾次
almost
差不多
I don't know how to count
不知道要算一下
But our new exhibit has about 10 billion new machine cells
但是我們的新展覽大概有100億顆新機細胞
Did you have it just now please come please
剛才是不是有 拜來 請
I want to ask the teacher
我想請問老師一下
That is to say, various cells differentiated from ESC and IPS
就是說 ESC跟IPS所分化出來的各種細胞
There seems to be some differences
好像還是有一些差異
don't know say such a difference
不知道說這樣的差異
where is the difference
差異到底在什麼地方
Cells differentiated from true IPS
真的IPS分化出來的細胞
It can really be used for clinical application
真的可以拿來臨床應用
ok thanks for your question
好 謝謝你的問題
That is, wearing stem cells
就是說 佩戴幹細胞
Derived new machine cells or nerve cells
衍生出來的新機細胞或神經細胞
Turn blood into IPS
跟拿抽血變成IPS
Derived new machine cells and nerve cells
衍生出來的新機細胞跟神經細胞
what's the difference
到底有什麼多大的不同
cannot replace
不能來代替
Everyone's results are different
這個每一個人做出來的結果都不太一樣
so there's no judging yet
所以現在還沒有定論
The simplest answer is this
最簡單的回答是這樣子
No matter what, back to the origin is still the same
不管怎麼樣回到原點還是一樣
That is to say
也就是說
the purpose of that part
那部分這樣子做的目的
We hope to be personalized medicine
我們希望是個人化的醫療為主
You can imagine that we are doing about two hundred
各位可以想像我們在做大概有兩百多
about two hundred
兩百位左右
We all look different
我們每個人其實長得都不一樣
so you can imagine
所以你可以想像得到
Each of us has a different heart
我們每一個的心臟都不一樣
Each of us is genetically different
我們每一個人的基因都不一樣
so it's hard for you to say
所以你很難說
You use one cell to have an effect on everyone
你用一個細胞來對每一個人都有作用
even if you are a
甚至於你即使是一個
have been clinically tested
已經被臨床試驗
I have been taking the medicine for twenty years
已經做了已經吃了二十年的藥
Everyone's reaction may still be different
每一個人的反應都還是可能不太一樣
That creature is actually very complicated
那生物其實是很複雜的
I studied a medical engineering myself
我自己唸了一個醫工
Doctor of Medicine
醫工的博士
He also worked as a postdoctoral fellow at MIT for several years
他在MIT也做了幾年的博士後
deep feeling
體會很深究
In fact, there is a big difference between biology and engineering.
其實生物跟工程其實真的有很大的差別
Biology is far more complex than engineering
生物的複雜性遠遠超過工程
for example
舉個例子
For example, I used to be in Seattle
比如說我以前在西雅圖
Everyone knows Boeing
大家知道波音公司
He was flying in Seattle
他坐飛機就是在西雅圖
That Boeing 747
那一台波音747
He has 30,000 parts
他有三萬個零件好了
We probably have about 30,000 genes in that person
那人我們大概也有三萬個基因左右
That's it
這樣說好了
Those 30,000 Boeing 747 parts
那三萬個波音747的零件
if everything is complete
如果都齊全了
experienced engineer
有經驗的工程師
There are engineers and blueprints
有工程師有藍圖
spell it out
把它拼做起來
Come on, maybe you can drive and fly
加油 可能就可以開就可以飛
But 30,000 genes
可是三萬個基因
Makes 30,000 proteins
做成三萬個蛋白質
In the past, one gene and one protein
以前是說一個基因一個蛋白質
but it's not that simple
可是沒有那麼簡單
Sometimes several genes and one protein
有時候是好幾個基因一個蛋白質
Sometimes one gene and several proteins
有時候是一個基因好幾個蛋白質
leave it alone
不管它
Thirty thousand genes count as three eggs
三萬個基因就算做三個蛋
Thirty thousand proteins
三萬個蛋白質
as if we put
就好像我們把
Thirty thousand people locked in one room
三萬個人關在一間房間裡面
someone is sleeping
有人在睡覺
someone is eating
有人在吃飯
someone is chatting
有人在聊天
someone is playing
有人在打球
Everyone reacts differently
每一個人的反應通通都不一樣
it produces these
它所產生的這些
All combinations of pairings
所有的組合的配對
Absolutely more than 30,000 parts
絕對超過三萬個零件
lie there without moving
躺在那裡不會動
in terms of complexity
就複雜度
so this is a creature
所以這個是生物
It's very different from an engineer
跟工程師是很不一樣的
Even if we have put
我們就算已經把
Human Genome Project
Human Genome Project
Complete the decoding of human genes
把人的基因的解碼都弄好了
you have to study it
你要把它研究
don't say in a hundred years
不要說在一百年
maybe in a thousand years
可能在一千年
we still only know
我們還是只知道
very small portion
很小的部分
Of course what you do now must be much better
當然現在做的必然是好很多
you ask me now
你現在問我說
These cells derived from ESL
跟ESL所衍生出來的這些細胞
How big is the difference
它的差異到底多大
I think this is still case by case
我覺得這個還是case by case
It is more important to return to their respective
還是回到各自的比較重要
come please
來 請
thank you teacher
謝謝老師請問一下
Just now you mentioned that there are new
剛剛你提到在這一些有新
new long-term disease
新長級病的
We are in prime time for four days
我們在四天的黃金時間內
can do a reminder
可以來做一個催門
a practical problem
一個實際面對的問題
in four days
就在四天之內
I'm afraid it will be too late
恐怕會緩不及急
If you use autologous this
如果是用autologous的這個
cell words
cell的話
words of limb cells
肢體細胞的話
you have to go through
你還要經過
calculation,calculation,calculation
calculation,calculation,calculation
Then also check that it is in the
然後還檢驗它有沒有在
The whole domination process has contamination
整個支配過程有contamination的
this problem
這個問題
this is a consideration
這個是一個考量
the second one is
那第二個就是
If we use Algenic
如果我們用Algenic
These cells are like the Japanese JGC day meeting company
這些細胞像日本JGC日會公司
They're also doing this cell-forming
他們也在做這種細胞成
We use mass production
我們用mass production的方式
or edic
或是edic
It should be a word back
該是包了一個字背
then stole it
然後把它stole
This is expected to learn from the material of cells
這個是跟細胞的材料期待學
or other different
或者是其他不一樣
He's like this because he's also a drug dealer
他因為他也是一個藥品之計這樣子
I think these two considerations
我想這兩個考量點
I don't know what you think Mr. Xie
不知道謝老師你的看法
I may not have explained clearly just now
我剛剛可能沒有解釋得很清楚
Our technology is grounded from the patient
我們的技術是從病人磨倒之後
Whoever pulls the bone, kisses the water and pours it in
抽骨誰 吻水澆再打進去
The whole process takes about an hour and a half
整個過程大概是一個半小時
No need to culture cells, no need to move, no need
不需要培養細胞 不需要動都不需要
So there's no need for those
所以其實不需要那些
So there is no such problem in time
所以時間上是沒有這個問題
But if there is Alogenic, it is the issue
但是如果有Alogenic就是議題的
The issue is that people are the same
議題就是說一樣是人
but not other animals
但是不是別的動物
but different people
但是是不同的人
if we can
如果我們的確可以
store all his cells
把他的細胞都儲存起來
He will be available in the future
他將來馬上可以用
This is of course a better way
這當然是一個比較好的辦法
Actually that's all
實際上這也是所有的
Biotech companies owned by pharmaceutical companies
藥廠所有的生技公司
cell therapy companies their approach
細胞治療公司他們的approach
Only in this way can we sell
因為這樣子才能夠去賣
However, one must also consider that
不過也必須要考量一點就是說
the same
一樣就
Different Diseases Different Cells
不同的疾病不同的細胞
it has different pros and cons
它有不同的優缺點
for example
譬如說
Of course, what it does more often is stick to stem cells
當然它比較常做的是堅持幹細胞
Stick to stem cells no matter where they come from
不管是從哪裡來的堅持幹細胞
Stick to stem cells it has great benefits
堅持幹細胞它有很大的好處
It can be cultivated in large quantities
它可以大量的培養
You can move it and use it one by one
可以動起來一管一管的用
It is also very organized
它的組織能力也很強
Adhere to stem cells, there are many studies that say
堅持幹細胞也有很多的研究說
an immune response that does not produce too severe
對不會產生太嚴重的免疫的反應
so it sounds like everything is fine
所以聽起來好像什麼都很好
But insisting on stem cells has its limits
可是堅持幹細胞也有它的局限
Because sticking to stem cells it mainly grows into bone
因為堅持幹細胞它主要是長成骨頭
It is easier to grow into cartilage or fat cells
長成軟骨或者長成脂肪細胞比較容易
to grow elsewhere
要長成其他的地方
That is to say, you need to rely on this to persist in stem cells
就是說你要靠這個堅持幹細胞
become cardiomyocytes
變成心肌細胞
become nerve cells
變成神經細胞
Or maybe it's harder to become a liver cell
或者變成肝臟細胞大概比較難
In fact, many people think that it is not
其實很多人是認為是不會
I even said that I knew it very early in the animal room
甚至於說在動物室很早就知道
That is to say, you inject persistent stem cells into the heart
就是說你把堅持幹細胞打到心臟裡面去
Although it can secrete
它雖然可以分泌
Growth factors grow blood vessels
生長因子長出血管
But he also grows bones
可是他也會長骨頭
Then you want to inject stem cells into the heart to treat myocardial infarction
那你希望拿幹細胞打到心臟來治療心肌梗塞
Although he will grow blood vessels
他雖然會長出血管
but he has bones
可是他長骨頭
You probably don't want to grow bones in your heart
你大概不希望在你的心臟裡面長骨頭
So actually every kind of
所以其實每一種的
indication is still different
indication還是有他不同的
problem must be considered
問題必須要去考慮
But in terms of part-time stem cells
但是從兼職幹細胞來講
He can be mass-bred out of the village
他可以被大量培養出村
he does have his great strengths
他的確有他很大的優點
Although we say
我們雖然說
Autologous does not need to consider the problem of immune rejection
自體的不用考慮免疫排斥的問題
And then pretty fast
然後也蠻快的
but we also have our problems
但我們也有我們的問題
For example very simple
譬如說很簡單的
Many patients are
很多病人就是因為
His bone marrow cells are not good
他的骨髓細胞不好
It's just that his ability to grow blood vessels is not good.
就是他長血管的能力不好
He will have a myocardial infarction
他才會心肌梗塞
what will happen
才會怎麼樣
Then you do it with his cells
那你再拿他的細胞來做
Although we have given a good way
雖然我們給了很好的方式
I can't guarantee that he will have a good result.
不敢保證他一定會有很好的結果
like we're doing animal experiments
像我們在做動物實驗
Actually doing pig like this
其實在做豬這樣子
So these actually take some time
所以這些其實都還要一些時間
to come and prove
才能過來證明說
which one will be better
到底哪一個會是比較好
Better
比較好
But I think biomedical
不過我想生物醫學
Especially the progress of clinical medicine
尤其是臨床醫學的進步
Sometimes it takes a long time to develop
有時候的確是需要滿長的時間去發展
Now for these results
現在來講這些結果
Who will be the best in the future
將來誰哪一個是會最好
It may take a while to understand
可能還有需要一段時間才會比較了解
but you must do
不過你一定得做
Otherwise these patients have no hope
要不然這些病人其實是沒有希望
no chance
沒有機會的
And a patient with a heart attack
而且一個心機梗塞的病人
I probably didn't mention it just now.
我剛剛可能沒有特別提就是
Although most of us in Taiwan
雖然說我們在台灣大多數的
As long as it is a place above a medium-sized city
只要是中等城市以上的地方
patients with myocardial infarction
心機梗塞的病人
Once sent to the emergency room
一旦被送到急診
Can open blood vessels in 90 minutes
都可以在90分鐘內把血管打開
But don't forget to say
可是不要忘了就是說
Myocardial infarction has about one-third of the patients
心機梗塞本來就有三分之一左右的病人
No chance of receiving these treatments at all
根本沒有機會接受這些治療
it passes
它就過去了
Even a patient is lucky
即使是一個病人很幸運的
He can in the fastest time
他可以在最快的時間之內
Open up the blood vessels
把血管打通
A day or two in an AC ward
在交流病房住一兩天
transfer to general ward
轉到普通病房
then went home
然後就回家了
Nearly one in five such patients
有將近五分之一這樣的病人
Go home after these best treatments
經過這些最好的治療也可以回家
Three months back or new failure
三個月回來還是新衰竭
Because he had a relatively large myocardial infarction
因為他的心機梗塞範圍比較大
The moment of his heart attack had already sealed his fate
在他心機梗塞那一剎那已經決定他的命運了
Some of these patients are quite young in their 30s and 40s.
這些病人他有些還蠻年輕才三四十歲
But for the rest of his life, he spent decades in new exhaustion
但是他後半輩子幾十年的時間都是新衰竭
There are actually a lot of patients
這樣病人其實不少
so one-fifth, almost one-fifth
這樣五分之一 將近五分之一
The whole world is the same, so is Taiwan
全世界都一樣 台灣也是這樣子
There is currently no treatment for these patients
這些病人目前沒有什麼治療的方式
It's you, just give the strength agent, the cardiotonic agent
就是你就給力料劑 給強心劑
Give the angiodysplasia agent this treatment
給血管素障劑這樣治療
Patients with these treatments help
這些治療的病人幫助
He's just delaying, just treating the symptoms.
他只是延緩而已 只是症狀治療
It doesn't really help his heart function much.
對他的心臟功能其實沒有太大幫助
So in the end he still has to go until the heart grows bigger
所以最後他還是要走到心臟變大
to transplant this path
要移植這條路
What we hope is to be able to help such patients
我們希望的是能夠幫助這樣的病人
so these
所以這些
What is being done now is to develop these technologies and these treatments
現在在做的發展這些技術這些治療
In fact, many large parts
其實很多很大的部分
is here to help these
是在來幫助這些
I met the need to indication
I met the need to indication
including what we just
包括我們剛才
Talk about the next ischemic patient
講那個下次缺血的病人
ok one last question
好 最後一個問題好了
Ask Mr. Xie
請教謝老師
The Egyptian on the Chinese lion
那個文獅上裡面那個埃及
The Egyptians made Aunt Mulan to take out the glandular organs for extra processing
埃及人做那個木蘭姨是把腺臟拿出來額外處理
There is no physiological meaning in it, except that they produce blood
這裡面有代表什麼生理的意義除了他們生血
This other eye problem is
這另外一個眼神問題是
Some people judge that brain shit is death
有些人判斷說腦屎是死亡
Some people say that the permanent stop of the glands is death
有些人說腺臟永遠停掉是死亡
Are these two correlations related?
這兩個相關是不是有相關性
The first question is easier for me to answer
第一個問題我比較容易回答
because i don't know sorry
因為我不知道 對不起
The second question we are judging
第二個問題我們在判
stop now, let's go
現在停下來一定過去吧
this is for sure
這個是一定的
But the brain shit we are talking about is actually different from the vegetative state
但是我們講的腦屎跟植物人狀態其實是不一樣的
Brain shit means that if you don’t actively give him these life support systems
腦屎的意思是說你要是沒有積極的給他這些維生的系統的時候
he is going to pass
他就要過去了
Then our general vegetative people don’t need any respirator
那我們一般植物人他可以不用任何的呼吸器
without any drugs or anything
不用任何的藥物什麼之類的
he can still lie there
他就是還是可以躺在那裡
So actually the two are not the same
所以其實這兩個是不太一樣的
We're doing tracheal transplants for brain-dead patients.
我們在做氣管移植是要腦死的病人
not pointing fingers
不是指負人
is that clear? yes
這樣清楚嗎?可以
Just now you...
剛才你...
what is it
是什麼?
The same factor makes the heart grow
一樣因素會讓心臟壯大
many reasons
很多原因
But the most common is myocardial infarction
但是最常見的還是心肌梗塞
Heart muscle grows for many reasons
很多原因會讓心肌壯大
myocardial infarction
心肌梗塞
slowly at most
慢慢的最多
But there are many, many types of heart disease
但心臟病其實有很多很多種
This talk can last a long time
這個講可以講很久
no myocardial infarction
在傳沒有心肌梗塞
will, will
會,也會
such as cardiomyopathy
比如說心肌症
It has congenital defects in its muscles
它肌肉本身有先天性的缺陷
Its heart will grow bigger and bigger
它的心臟就會越來越大
For example, after a long period of high blood pressure
比如說高血壓久了之後
The heart can compensate at first
心臟一開始還可以代償
If it doesn't work later, it will collapse like this
後來不行垮掉也會這樣子
Even a viral infection can give you cardiomyopathy
甚至於病毒感染也會讓你產生心肌症
It's not just closing arterial tissue and causing myocardial infarction.
不是只有關上動脈組織造成心肌梗塞會這樣
Yes, so will demonic diseases
會 伴魔性疾病也會
But this is less
但這個現在比較少
not obsessive
不是 伴魔性
It's a problem with the demon
就是伴魔出問題
give your heart a problem
讓你的心臟出問題
This is now less and less
這個現在已經越來越少了
Because the most common access to this is the previous
因為這個最常見的通往都是以前
caused by rheumatic fever
風濕熱引起的
When public health is poor
公共衛生做得比較不好的時候
For example, when you are twenty or thirty years old
比如說年輕二三十歲的時候
Infectious rheumatic fever not well controlled
感染的風濕熱沒有控制好
Slowly the companion demon becomes destructive
慢慢的伴魔就變得破壞
After ten or twenty years, I will change my partner
十年二十年之後就要換伴魔
This was very common in the past
這個在以前很常見
Thirty years ago we performed open heart surgery
三十年前的時候我們做開心手術
Seventy to eighty percent are changing companions
百分之七八十都是在換伴魔
Now less than one out of ten is changing companions
現在十個不到一個是在換伴魔
It's all headhunting now
現在都是在撈頭手術
not the same
不太一樣
exist
在
that already has a companion
那已經有伴魔的
it will be like this
它會就是這樣子
Can't change eyes
不能夠換眼
or already connected
或是已經連接
want to change connection
想換連接
it already has a companion
它已經有伴魔的人
Everyone has a companion
大家都有伴魔
There is no way without a companion
沒有伴魔就沒辦法
i keep saying that
我一直這樣說
a lot of hair bits a lot a lot
很多毛鑽頭很多很多
but already have these
但是已經有了這些
there is no ambulance
有沒有就沒有救護師
If your normal life situation
如果你的正常的生活狀況
or give a diuretic
或者給一點力尿劑
so that you can maintain a normal life
就可以讓你維持正常的生活
you can ignore him
你可以不用理他
but you have to always
但是你要常常
Follow up every three months
就每三個月要做一次追蹤
If your heart function starts to get worse
如果你的心臟功能開始變差
consider surgery
就要考慮做手術
That surgery usually we hope is
那做手術通常我們希望是
If you can repair it, try to repair it and don't replace it.
能夠修補就盡量修補不要換
Because the repair may only need two stitches.
因為修補可能只要縫兩針就好了
then if you change
那你如果換的話就會
the next question is
下一個問題就
Then you want to change the pig half mill?
那你到底要換豬半磨
half ground pork heart
豬心半磨
Your heart hair may need to be replaced with a metal half grinder
你的心髮或者要換金屬半磨
it has pros and cons
它各有利弊
At this time, different factors should be considered
這個時候就要考慮不同的因素了
I'm basically saying
我基本上就是說
Don't move the knife if you can
能夠不要動刀就不要動刀
It's you who rely on medication
就是你靠藥物治療
There is no way to solve your problem
已經沒辦法解決你的問題
you are still uncomfortable
你還是不舒服
If you're talking about
如果您現在講的是
your own situation
你自己的狀況
Ninety percent of my judgment is yours
我的判斷百分之九十就你
no knife needed
不需要動刀
Otherwise you wouldn't be like this
要不然你不會現在這樣子
can talk to me like this for so long
可以跟我這樣對談這麼久
You're half dehydrated and there's a new noise
你半磨脫水就會有新雜音
A new noise does not necessarily mean that there is a major problem
有新雜音不見得是代表有大問題
Might need
可能要
Make an appointment with Dr. Xie to visit National Taiwan University
跟謝醫師約一下去台大去看一看
I have an outpatient clinic at National Taiwan University Sina Surgery on Wednesday.
我禮拜三下我在台大新浪外科有門診
I didn't have to see a hundred patients like the vice president said
我沒有像副院長講的要看一百個病人
I suddenly won't have more than five patients
我突然不會超過五個病人
So you come and I can chat with you no problem
所以你來我還可以跟你聊天沒問題
Periodic physical examination is still required
定期身體檢查還是需要
well because of the time we have to be here
好因為這個時間的關係我們必須在這裡
just stop
就停
We thank Dr. Xie
我們感謝這個謝醫師
Research continues to strengthen our future of this biomedical
在研究繼續加強對我們未來這個生醫的
Whether it's treating diseases, etc.
不管是在治療疾病等等
we have great expectations thank you doctor
我們有很大的期待謝謝謝醫師
Thank you for your viewing
ご視聴ありがとうございました